<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1251"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY % global.entities SYSTEM
        "../../../include/global.xml">
    %global.entities;
]>
	<article lang="en">
	
	<articleinfo>
    <title>Proposal of MMORPG Ireon</title>
        
   	<releaseinfo>Version 1.1.0</releaseinfo>
        
    <abstract>
    <para>
        This document describes our game design philosophy, our 
        goals, and the differences between us and other mmorpgs. It 
        is the project's basic and briefest management document.
    </para>
    <para>
        If you have any questions, feel free to ask them at 
        project’s <ulink url="http://forum.ireon.org/" 
        >forum</ulink> or via e-mail <email>input@ireon.org</email>.
    </para>
    </abstract>
        
    <keywordset>
   	<keyword>ireon</keyword>
    <keyword>proposal</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    
    <copyright>
    	&copyrightinfo;
    </copyright>
    
    <legalnotice>
    	&legalnotice;
    </legalnotice>
    </articleinfo>
    
    <sect1 id="what_do_we_do">
    <title id="what_do_we_do.title">What do we do</title>
    <para>
        Our primary goal is to develop a multiplayer online
        three-dimensional RPG, a client-server persistent virtual 
        world.
    </para>
    <para>
        The game is to be played through the Internet. The virtual 
        allocated server will be rented for the game. Playing the 
        game will be free of charge for all users.
    </para>
    <para>
        Ireon is an open source software, full source code is going 
        to be available through GPL license.
    </para>
    
    <sect2 id="platform">
    <title id="platform.title">The platform</title>
    <para>
        The game is going to be developed for the PC platform. 
        Development for other platforms currently is not planned. 
        Developers will support the client for Windows OS, and 
        server for FreeBSD. Developers will not support any other 
        systems, but will help anyone who's willing to do it.
	</para>
	<para>
        Hardware requirements for client and server parts will be 
        described later in the <ulink 
        url="http://www.ireon.org/en/docs/html/srs/index.html" 
        >Software Requirements Specification</ulink>. Requirements 
        should be relatively low to ensure wide accessibility 
        (potential new developers included).
	</para>
    </sect2>
    <!-- /The platform -->
    
    <sect2 id="audience">
    <title id="audience.title">The audience</title>
    <para>
        The game is designed for the players who are at least 14 
        years old. The game is intended for the English- and 
        Russian-speaking markets (developers will support both 
        English and Russian versions), that's why we are going to 
        keep in mind opportunities for fairly simple localizations 
        from the very beginning of development. 
    </para>
    <para>
        The world is designed for moderate and moderately hardcore 
        players. Players should have basic knowledge of RPGs and 
        online games. The game is not designed for hardcore lovers 
        of any specific RPG systems or games.
    </para>
    <para>
        Our increased attention to social and exploring parts of 
        virtual worlds hopefully will attract some additional 
        players from MUDs and browser-based online games.
    </para>
    </sect2>
    <!-- /The audience -->
    
    <sect2 id="similar_worlds">
    <title id="similar_worlds.title">Worlds out there</title>
    <para>
        Some virtual worlds that share certain features with us:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    	<ulink url="http://www.worldofwarcraft.com/">World of 
    	Warcraft</ulink> &mdash; a large-scale commercial world 
    	similar in concept and style (server-client model, 
    	three-dimensional world, real time play, fantasy setting, 
    	etc.)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    	<ulink url="http://www.lineage2.com/">Lineage II</ulink> 
    	&mdash; in the same way as World of Warcraft
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.planeshift.it/">Planeshift</ulink> 
        &mdash; open source code
   	</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.3sider.com/">3sider</ulink> &mdash; a 
        browser-based game where players affect global world 
        situation by their actions
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.pentacore.ru/">Pentacore</ulink> 
        &mdash; a browsed-based game that has politics and 
        territories under control of different factions
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <!-- /Worlds out there -->
    
    <sect2 id="releaze_time">
    <title id="releaze_time.title">When is release</title>
    <para>
        You can find information about planned playable release date 
        in the <ulink 
        url="http://www.ireon.org/en/docs/html/spmp.html" >Software 
        Project Management Plan</ulink>.
   	</para>
    </sect2>
    <!-- /When is release -->
    
    <sect2 id="our_goals">
    <title id="our_goals.title">Our goals</title>
    <para>
        Our goal is research and development (r&amp;d) in game 
        design, game programming and organization of distributed 
        game development process. Certain project members may have 
        other goals such as meeting new people or the world conquest 
        :)
     </para>
     </sect2>
     <!-- /Our goals -->
        
    <sect2 id="metrics">
   	<title id="metrics.title">The metrics</title>
    <para>
        We are going to consider the project successful if:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        we have a detailed software requirements specification (two 
        hundred pages excluding tables and so forth);
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    	we develop and document (in a software project management 
    	plan and similar papers) development methodology and define 
    	and test tools for a smooth development process;
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        at least one game server is always online with at 
        least 70-100 players online.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <!-- /The metrics -->
    
    </sect1>
    <!-- /What do we do -->
    
    <sect1 id="problem">
    <title id="problem.title">The problem</title>
    <para>
        Nowadays the majority of large-scale client-server online 
        RPGs are action-oriented worlds (Korean games are especially 
        good examples of that). That is, they are designed mostly 
        for those players who like fights, ratings, and 
        tournaments.
    </para>
    <para>
        On the other hand, surveys and studies (for example, see 
        Nick Yee's <ulink 
        url="http://www.nickyee.com/daedalus/">Daedalus</ulink> 
        project) show that not all players are willing to have 
        exactly this kind of life in a virtual world. Moreover, in 
        our opinion a number of people who mostly want to socialize 
        and interact greatly exceeds a number of action-lovers, but 
        none of those people are taken into account in existing 
        games.
    </para>
    <para>
        There are some RPGs for those 'others'. For example <ulink 
        url="http://www.atitd.com/">A Tale in the Desert</ulink> is 
        designed mostly for explorer-type players and <ulink 
        url="http://www.secondlife.com/">Second Life</ulink> is 
        designed mostly for socializers. And certainly there are 
        hundreds of MUDs each giving innumerable options for 
        roleplaying and socializing. But all these worlds can not be 
        considered popular when seen against large commercial 
        'action' projects. In our POV, this is because of their flat 
        learning curve (which is actually a bad thing opposite to 
        the popular misapprehension), poor usability, and poor 
        quality of service.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <!-- /The problem -->
    
    <sect1 id="our_solution">
    <title id="our_solution.title">Our solution</title>
    <para>
        The ultimate goal of our project is to combine highly varied 
        and interesting gameplay from MUDs with human-friendly 
        interface and easily understandable visuals of client-server 
        RPGs. Our core aims are easy socializing and rich gameplay 
        (where 'rich' means the roles of warrior and battle mage are 
        not the only ones possible).
    </para>
    <para>
        Here are examples of specific game roles for 
        non-fighters-like players:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        trader and crafter for explorers;
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        politician and journalist for socializers.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        But for all that openness and playing free of charge are not 
        considered as key player-attracting factors. Openness of 
        project is first and foremost needed for attracting new 
        developers.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <!-- /Our solution -->
    
    <sect1 id="us_and_them">
    <title id="us_and_them.title">The differences between us and 
    other projects</title>
    <para>
        Our core difference from similar projects is gameplay based 
        on needs of players, not dreams of developers. Our team is 
        not a <emphasis>group of gamers</emphasis> that decided to 
        develop 'a better World of Warcraft with more mobs'. In our 
        work we are guided by studies and experience of leading 
        experts in development of virtual worlds (you can find a 
        list of recommended reading at our site). We pay special 
        attention to usability and easy acquaintance of players with 
        concepts of our world.
    </para>
    <para>
        So, to sum up what do we have:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        efficient management &mdash; we place high emphasis on 
        development process, methodology, tools, documents, etc.;
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        responsible approach &mdash; we study and draw on experience 
        of other developers (e.g. using third-party software like 
        Ogre engine);
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        steady workflow &mdash; our work does not depend on 
        spontaneous enthusiasm of project's members, but is a 
        continous process;
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        highest possible openness (code included) that continually 
        attracts new developers.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <!-- /The difference between us and other projects -->
    
    <sect1 id="what_read_next">
    <title id="what_read_next.title">What to read next</title>
    <para>
    	If you are interested in project's management, next 
    	document you should read is probably the <ulink 
    	url="http://www.ireon.org/en/docs/html/spmp.html">Software 
    	Project Management Plan</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
        If you want to learn about Ireon's game design, the place to 
        begin is the <ulink 
        url="http://www.ireon.org/en/docs/html/concept.html">Concept 
        Document</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
        If you are not exactly sure what do you want to read next, 
        our <ulink 
        url="http://bugtraq.ireon.org/wiki/en/Tutorials/Docs" 
        >Documentaion Guide</ulink> may help you to make up your 
        mind.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <!-- /What to read next -->
    
	</article>
	<!-- /Proposal of MMORPG Ireon -->