<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1251"?>

<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
  [
    <!ENTITY % global.entities SYSTEM
        "../../../include/global.xml">
    %global.entities;
  ]
>

<article lang="en">

  <articleinfo>

    <title>
      	Hearts, Clubs, Diamonds, Spades: Players Who Suit MUDs
    </title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Richard A.</firstname>
      <surname>Bartle</surname>
    </author>
    
    <copyright>
      <holder>Richard A. Bartle</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>
          All rights reserved.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

  <abstract>
  <para>
  	  <ulink url= "http://www.mud.co.uk/richard/hcds.htm" >Hearts, 
  	  Clubs, Diamonds, Spades: Players Who Suit MUDs</ulink>
  </para>
  <para>
      Four approaches to playing MUDs are identified and described. 
      These approaches may arise from the inter-relationship of two 
      dimensions of playing style: action versus interaction, and 
      world-oriented versus player-oriented. An account of the 
      dynamics of player populations is given in terms of these 
      dimensions, with particular attention to how to promote 
      balance or equilibrium. This analysis also offers an 
      explanation for the labelling of MUDs as being either "social" 
      or "gamelike".
  </para>
  </abstract>

  </articleinfo>


  <sect1 id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>
  <para>
      Most MUDs can trace their lineage directly back to Trubshaw's 
      1978 game<footnote><para>Bartle, R. A. (1990). Interactive 
      Multi-Player Computer Games. MUSE Ltd, Colchester, Essex, UK 
      <ulink url= 
      "ftp://ftp.lambda.moo.mud.org/pub/MOO/papers/mudreport.txt" 
      >Interactive Multi-User Computer Games</ulink> | 
      Burka, L. P. (1995). The MUDline.</para></footnote> and, 
      perhaps because of this heritage, the vast majority are 
      regarded as "games" by their "players". For the convenience of 
      its readers, this paper continues to view MUDs in this 
      tradition; however, it should be noted that MUDs can be of 
      considerable value in non-game (ie. "serious") 
      applications<footnote><para>Bruckman, A. S. (1994). Workshop: 
      "Serious" Uses of MUDs? Proc. DIAC-94 | Kort, B. (1991). The 
      MUSE as an Educational Medium BBN Labs, Cambridge, 
      Massachusetts | Bruckman, A. S. &amp; Resnick, M. (1993). 
      Virtual Professional Community: Results from the MediaMOO 
      Project. MIT Media Laboratory, Cambridge, Massachusetts | 
      Curtis, P. &amp; Nichols, D. A. (1993). MUDs Grow Up: Social 
      Virtual Reality in the Real World. Xerox PARC, Palo Alto, 
      California 
      <ulink url= 
      "ftp://ftp.lambda.moo.mud.org/pub/MOO/papers/MUDsGrowUp.txt" 
      >MUDs Grow Up</ulink> |
      Evard, R. (1993). Collaborative Networked 
      Communication: MUDs as System Tools. Proc. LISA-93
      <ulink url=
      "http://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/remy/documents/cncmast.html"
      >Collaborative Networked Communication</ulink> |
      Fanderclai, T. F. (1995). MUDs in Education: New Environments, 
      New Pedagogies. Computer-Mediated Communication Magazine, 
      2(1), 8 | Riner, R. D. &amp; Clodius, J. A. (1995). Simulating 
      Future Histories: The NAU Solar System Simulation and Mars 
      Settlement. Anthropology &amp; Education Quarterly 
      26(1):95-104 | Moock, C. (1996). Virtual Campus at the 
      University of Waterloo.</para></footnote>.
  </para>
  <para>
      Indeed, the thrust of this paper emphasises those factors 
      which should be borne in mind when attempting to create a 
      stable MUD in general, whatever the application; it is only 
      the terminology which is that of "fun" MUDs, not the subject 
      matter. In any case, even those MUDs which are built, from the 
      ground up, to be absolutely straight are still treated by 
      users as if they were games in some respects, eg. by choosing 
      whimsical names rather than using their real 
      ones<footnote><para>Roush, W. (1993). The Virtual STS Centre 
      on MediaMOO: Issues and Challenges as Non-Technical Users 
      Enter Social Virtual Spaces. MIT Media Laboratory, Cambridge, 
      Massachusetts.</para></footnote>.
  </para>
  <para>
      It is worthwhile considering for a moment whether MUDs (as 
      they are generally played) really are games, or whether 
      they're something else. People have many recreational 
      activities available to them, and perhaps MUDs fit some other 
      category better? Looking up the word "game" in a dictionary of 
      synonyms<footnote><para>Urdang, L. &amp; Manser, M. (1980). 
      The Pan Dictionary of Synonyms and Antonyms Pan Reference, 
      London, UK.</para></footnote> elicits three related nouns: 
      "pastime", "sport" and "entertainment" (a fourth, "amusement", 
      is the general class of which the others are all examples). So 
      it might be useful to ask:
  </para>
  <para>
      Are MUDs
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
      games? Like chess, tennis, AD&amp;D?
  </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>
      pastimes? Like reading, gardening, cooking?
  </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>
      sports? Like huntin', shootin', fishin'?
  </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>
      entertainments? Like nightclubs, TV, concerts?
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
      Or are they a combination of all four? Perhaps individual 
      players even see the <emphasis>same</emphasis> MUD differently 
      from each another?
  </para>
  <para>
      These questions will be returned to at the end of this paper, 
      along with some proposed answers.
  </para>
  </sect1>
   
   
  
  	<sect1 id="simple_taxonomy">
    <title>A simple taxonomy</title>
    <para>
    	This work grew out of a long, heated discussion which ran 
    	from November 1989 to May 1990 between the wizzes (ie. 
    	highly experienced players, of rank wizard or witch) on one 
    	particular commercial MUD in the UK<footnote><para>Bartle, 
    	R. A. (1985). MUD2 [MUDDLE] MUSE Ltd, Colchester, Essex, 
    	UK</para></footnote>. The debate was sparked by the question 
    	"What do people want out of a MUD?", and comprised several 
    	hundred bulletin-board postings, some of considerable 
    	length, typically concerning what the players liked, what 
    	they didn't like, why they played, and changes they would 
    	like to see to "improve" the game. Some 15 individuals took 
    	a major part, with perhaps another 15 adding their comments 
    	from time to time; this comprised almost the entire set of 
    	active wizzes during that period. Although at times the 
    	debate became quite intense, never did it lapse into the 
    	flaming which typically ends most open-ended, multi-speaker, 
    	online discussions.
    </para>
    <para>
    	The fact that the people contributing to this argument were 
    	the most advanced players in a MUD which allowed 
    	player-killing might, on the face of it, be taken as 
    	evidence that they would probably prefer more "gamelike" 
    	aspects over "social" ones. However, this was not the case: 
    	the MUD in question had players of all types in it, even at 
    	wiz level. (Later in this paper, an analysis is given as to 
    	how such a MUD can come to be).
    </para>
    <para>
    	When the participants had finally run out of new things to 
    	say, it became time for me (as senior administrator) to 
    	summarise. Abstracting the various points that had been 
    	raised, a pattern emerged; people habitually found the same 
    	kinds of thing about the game "fun", but there were several 
    	(four, in fact) sub-groupings into which opinion divided. 
    	Most players leaned at least a little to all four, but each 
    	tended to have some particular overall preference. The 
    	summary was generally well received by those who had 
    	participated in the debate.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Note that although this MUD was one in which player-killing 
    	was allowed, the taxonomy which is about to be described 
    	does (as will be explained later) apply equally to "social" 
    	MUDs. The advice concerning changes which can be made to 
    	affect the player make-up of a MUD is, however, less useful 
    	to social MUDs, or to ones with a heavy role-playing 
    	component. Also, the original discussion concerned only 
    	non-administrative aspects of MUDding; people who might 
    	play MUDs to learn object-oriented programming, for example, 
    	are therefore not addressed by this paper.
    </para>
    <para>
    	The four things that people typically enjoyed personally 
    	about MUDs were:
    	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem><para>
        	Achievement within the game context. Players give 
        	themselves game-related goals, and vigorously set out to 
        	achieve them. This usually means accumulating and 
        	disposing of large quantities of high-value treasure, or 
        	cutting a swathe through hordes of mobiles (ie. monsters 
        	built in to the virtual world).
    	</para></listitem>
    	<listitem><para>
    		Exploration of the game. Players try to find out as much 
    		as they can about the virtual world. Although initially 
    		this means mapping its topology (ie. exploring the MUD's 
    		breadth), later it advances to experimentation with its 
    		physics (ie. exploring the MUD's depth).
    	</para></listitem>
    	<listitem><para>
    		Socialising with others. Players use the game's 
    		communicative facilities, and apply the role-playing 
    		that these engender, as a context in which to converse 
    		(and otherwise interact) with their fellow players.
    	</para></listitem>
    	<listitem><para>
    		Imposition upon others. Players use the tools provided 
    		by the game to cause distress to (or, in rare 
    		circumstances, to help) other players. Where permitted, 
    		this usually involves acquiring some weapon and applying 
    		it enthusiastically to the persona of another player in 
    		the game world.
    	</para></listitem>
      	</orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
    	So, labelling the four player types abstracted, we get: 
    	achievers, explorers, socialisers and killers. An easy way 
    	to remember these is to consider suits in a conventional 
    	pack of cards: achievers are Diamonds (they're always 
    	seeking treasure); explorers are Spades (they dig around for 
    	information); socialisers are Hearts (they empathise with 
    	other players); killers are Clubs (they hit people with 
    	them).
    </para>
    <para>
    	Naturally, these areas cross over, and players will often 
    	drift between all four, depending on their mood or current 
    	playing style. However, my experience having observed 
    	players in the light of this research suggests that many (if 
    	not most) players do have a primary style, and will only 
    	switch to other styles as a (deliberate or subconscious) 
    	means to advance their main interest.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Looking at each player type in more detail, then:
    </para>
    <para>
    	1) Achievers regard points-gathering and rising in levels as 
    	their main goal, and all is ultimately subserviant to this. 
    	Exploration is necessary only to find new sources of 
    	treasure, or improved ways of wringing points from it.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Socialising is a relaxing method of discovering what other 
    	players know about the business of accumulating points, that 
    	their knowledge can be applied to the task of gaining 
    	riches. Killing is only necessary to eliminate rivals or 
    	people who get in the way, or to gain vast amounts of points 
    	(if points are awarded for killing other players).
    </para>
    <para>
    	Achievers say things like:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            "I'm busy."
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        	"Sure, I'll help you. What do I get?"
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"So how do YOU kill the dragon, then?"
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"Only 4211 points to go!"
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
    	2) Explorers delight in having the game expose its internal 
    	machinations to them. They try progressively esoteric 
    	actions in wild, out-of-the-way places, looking for 
    	interesting features (ie. bugs) and figuring out how things 
    	work. Scoring points may be necessary to enter some next 
    	phase of exploration, but it's tedious, and anyone with half 
    	a brain can do it.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Killing is quicker, and might be a constructive exercise in 
    	its own right, but it causes too much hassle in the long run 
    	if the deceased return to seek retribution. Socialising can 
    	be informative as a source of new ideas to try out, but most 
    	of what people say is irrelevant or old hat. The real fun 
    	comes only from discovery, and making the most complete set 
    	of maps in existence.
    </para>
    <para>
      	Explorers say things like:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"Hmm..."
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"You mean you don't know the shortest route from 
          	&lt;obscure room one&gt; to &lt;obscure room two&gt;?"
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"I haven't tried that one, what's it do?"
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"Why is it that if you carry the uranium you get 
          	radiation sickness, and if you put it in a bag you still 
          	get it, but if you put it in a bag and drop it then wait 
          	20 seconds and pick it up again, you don't?"
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
    	3) Socialisers are interested in people, and what they have 
    	to say. The game is merely a backdrop, a common ground where 
    	things happen to players. Inter-player relationships are 
    	important: empathising with people, sympathising, joking, 
    	entertaining, listening; even merely observing people play 
    	can be rewarding &mdash; seeing them grow as individuals, 
    	maturing 
    	over time. 
    </para>
    <para>
    	Some exploration may be necessary so as to understand what 
    	everyone else is talking about, and points-scoring could be 
    	required to gain access to neat communicative spells 
    	available only to higher levels (as well as to obtain a 
    	certain status in the community).
    </para>
    <para> 
    	Killing, however, is something only ever to be excused if 
    	it's a futile, impulsive act of revenge, perpetrated upon 
    	someone who has caused intolerable pain to a dear friend. 
    	The only ultimately fulfilling thing is not how to rise 
    	levels or kill hapless drips; it's getting to know people, 
    	to undertand them, and to form beautiful, lasting 
    	relationships.
    </para>
    <para>
      	Socialisers say things like:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"Hi!"
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"Yeah, well, I'm having trouble with my boyfriend."
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"What happened? I missed it, I was talking."
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"Really? Oh no! Gee, that's terrible! Are you sure? 
          	Awful, just awful!"
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
    	4) Killers get their kicks from imposing themselves on 
    	others. This may be "nice", ie. busybody do-gooding, but few 
    	people practice such an approach because the rewards (a 
    	warm, cosy inner glow, apparently) aren't very substantial. 
    	Much more commonly, people attack other players with a view 
    	to killing off their personae (hence the name for this style 
    	of play). The more massive the distress caused, the greater 
    	the killer's joy at having caused it. 
    </para>
    <para>
    	Normal points-scoring 
    	is usually required so as to become powerful enough to begin 
    	causing havoc in earnest, and exploration of a kind is 
    	necessary to discover new and ingenious ways to kill people. 
    	Even socialising is sometimes worthwhile beyond taunting a 
    	recent victim, for example in finding out someone's playing 
    	habits, or discussing tactics with fellow killers. They're 
    	all just means to an end, though; only in the knowledge that 
    	a real person, somewhere, is very upset by what you've just 
    	done, yet can themselves do nothing about it, is there any 
    	true adrenalin-shooting, juicy fun.
    </para>
	<para>
      	Killers says things like:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"Ha!"
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"Coward!"
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"Die!"
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          	"Die! Die! Die!"
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
	<para>
		(Killers are people of few words).
	</para>
	<para>
		How many players typically fall within each area depends on 
		the MUD. If, however, too many gravitate to one particular 
		style, the effect can be to cause players of other 
		persuasions to leave, which in turn may feed back and reduce 
		the numbers in the first category. For example, too many 
		killers will drive away the achievers who form their main 
		prey; this in turn will mean that killers will stop playing, 
		as they'll have no worthwhile victims (players considered by 
		killers to be explorers generally don't care about death, 
		and players considered to be socialisers are too easy to 
		pose much of a challenge). These direct relationships are 
		discussed in more detail towards the end of this paper.
	</para>
    <para>
    	For the most part, though, the inter-relationships between 
    	the various playing styles are more subtle: a sharp 
    	reduction in the number of explorers for whatever reason 
    	could mean a gradual reduction in achievers, who get bored 
    	if they're not occasionally told of different hoops they can 
    	jump through for points; this could affect the number of 
    	socialisers (the fewer players there are, the less there is 
    	to talk about), and it would certainly lower the killer 
    	population (due to a general lack of suitable victims).
    </para>
    <para>
    	Making sure that a game doesn't veer off in the wrong 
    	direction and lose players can be difficult; administrators 
    	need to maintain a balanced relationship between the 
    	different types of players, so as to guarantee their MUD's 
    	"feel". Note that I am not advocating any particular form of 
    	equilibrium: it is up to the game administrators themseles 
    	to decide what atmosphere they want their MUD to have, and 
    	thus define the point at which it is "balanced" (although 
    	the effort required to maintain this desired state could be 
    	substantial).
    </para>
    <para>
    	Later, this paper considers means by which a MUD can be 
    	pushed in different directions, either to restore an earlier 
    	balance between the player types, to define a new target set 
    	of relationships between the player types, or to cause the 
    	interplay between the player types to break down entirely. 
    	However, first a means is required of formally linking the 
    	four principal playing styles into aspects of a unified 
    	whole; this helps account for different degrees of adherence 
    	to particular styles, and aids visualisation of what 
    	"altering the balance" of a MUD might actually mean.
    </para>
  	</sect1>
  
  
  	<sect1 id="interest_graph">
    <title>Interest graph</title>
	<para>
		Consider the following abstract graph: 
    </para>
    	<figure id="en_hcds_1">
              <title>Interest graph</title>
              <graphic
                fileref="figures/en_hcds_1.gif"/>
            </figure>
    <para>
    	The axes of the graph represent the source of players' 
    	interest in a MUD. The x-axis goes from an emphasis on 
    	players (left) to an emphasis on the environment (right); 
    	the y-axis goes from acting with (bottom) to acting on 
    	(top). The four extreme corners of the graph show the four 
    	typical playing preferences associated with each quadrant. 
    	To see how the graph works, it is appropriate to consider 
    	each of the four styles in detail:
    </para>
    <para>
    	1) Achievers are interested in doing things to the game, ie. 
    	in ACTING on the WORLD. It's the fact that the game 
    	environment is a fully-fledged world in which they can 
    	immerse themselves that they find compelling; its being 
    	shared with other people merely adds a little authenticity, 
    	and perhaps a competitive element. The point of playing is 
    	to master the game, and make it do what you want it to do; 
    	there's nothing intrinsically worthwhile in rooting out 
    	irrelevant details that will never be of use, or in idling 
    	away your life with gossip.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Achievers are proud of their formal status in the game's 
    	built-in level hierarchy, and of how short a time they took 
    	to reach it.
    </para>
    <para>
    	2) Explorers are interested in having the game surprise 
    	them, ie. in INTERACTING with the WORLD. It's the sense of 
    	wonder which the virtual world imbues that they crave for; 
    	other players add depth to the game, but they aren't 
    	essential components of it, except perhaps as sources of new 
    	areas to visit. Scoring points all the time is a worthless 
    	occupation, because it defies the very open-endedness that 
    	makes a world live and breathe. Most accomplished explorers 
    	could easily rack up sufficient points to reach the top, but 
    	such one-dimensional behaviour is the sign of a limited 
    	intellect.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Explorers are proud of their knowledge of the game's finer 
    	points, especially if new players treat them as founts of 
    	all knowledge.
    </para>
    <para>
    	3) Socialisers are interested in INTERACTING with other 
    	PLAYERS. This usually means talking, but it can extend to 
    	more exotic behaviour. Finding out about people and getting 
    	to know them is far more worthy than treating them as fodder 
    	to be bossed around. The game world is just a setting; it's 
    	the characters that make it so compelling.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Socialisers are proud of their friendships, their contacts 
    	and their influence.
    </para>
    <para>
    	4) Killers are interested in doing things to people, ie. in 
    	ACTING on other PLAYERS. Normally, this is not with the 
    	consent of these "other players" (even if, objectively, the 
    	interference in their play might appear "helpful"), but 
    	killers don't care; they wish only to demonstrate their 
    	superiority over fellow humans, preferably in a world which 
    	serves to legitimise actions that could mean imprisonment in 
    	real life. Accumulated knowledge is useless unless it can be 
    	applied; even when it is applied, there's no fun unless it 
    	can affect a real person instead of an emotionless, 
    	computerised entity.
    </para>
    <para>
    	The "interest graph" is a representational structure which 
    	can chart what players find of interest in a MUD. The axes 
    	can be assigned a relative scale reflecting the ratio of an 
    	individual's interest between the two extremes that it 
    	admits. Thus, for example, someone who thinks that the 
    	people who are in the world are maybe twice as important as 
    	the the world itself would lie on a vertical line 
    	intersecting the x-axis at a point one 1/6 of the distance 
    	from the origin to the left edge; if they had little 
    	interest in bending the game to their will, preferring their 
    	actions to have some give and take, then they would also lie 
    	on a horizontal line at the bottom of the y-axis. The 
    	interesection of the two lines would put them in the 
    	socialiser quadrant, with leanings to explorer.
    </para>
    <para>
    	It is, of course, possible to analyse the behaviour of 
    	individual players quantitatively by processing transcripts 
    	of their games. Unfortunately, this is very difficult to do 
    	except for very limited domains (eg. forms of 
    	communication<footnote><para>Cherny, L. (1995). The Modal 
    	Complexity of Speech Events in a Social MUD. Electronic 
    	Journal of Communication, Summer 1995. The Situated 
    	Behaviour of MUD Back Channels. Dept. Linguistics, Stanford 
    	University, California.</para></footnote>). An alternative 
    	approach might simply be to ask the players what they 
    	themselves like about a particular MUD: even a short 
    	questionnaire, completed anonymously, can give a fair 
    	indication of what players find 
    	enjoyable<footnote><para>Emert, H. G. (1993). "X" Marks the 
    	Spot. East Stroudsburg University, 
    	Pennsylvania.</para></footnote>.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Such information can then be used to determine the make-up 
    	of the MUD's player base, so that in times of falling player 
    	numbers the current composition could be compared against 
    	some earlier ideal, and remedial action taken to redress the 
    	imbalance. This "ideal" configuration would, however, be 
    	specific to that particular MUD, and its precise form is 
    	therefore not addressed here. Instead, the more general 
    	issue of how to alter the balance between player types is 
    	considered, along with the gross effects that can be 
    	expected to follow from having done so.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
    
    <sect1 id="changing_balance">
  	<title>Changing the player type balance</title>
    <para>
    	A stable MUD is one in which the four principal styles of 
    	player are in equilibrium. This doesn't imply that there are 
    	the same number of players exhibiting each style; rather, it 
    	means that over time the proportion of players for each 
    	style remains roughly constant, so that the balance between 
    	the the various types remains the same. Other factors are 
    	important, to do with the rate at which new players arrive 
    	and overall player numbers, but their consideration is not 
    	within the brief of this paper; the interaction between 
    	players of different types is within its brief, however, and 
    	is discussed in some detail later.
    </para>
    <para>
    	The actual point of balance (ie. whereabouts in the interest 
    	graph the centre of gravity of the individual players' 
    	points lies) can vary quite enormously; it is up to 
    	individual administrators to determine where they want it to 
    	lie, and to make any programming or design changes necessary 
    	to ensure that this is where it actually does. What kind of 
    	strategies, though, can be employed to achieve this task?
    </para>
    <para>
    	In order to answer this question, consider the interest 
    	graph. If it is regarded as a plane in equilibrium, it can 
    	be tilted in a number of ways to favour different areas. 
    	Usually, this will be at the expense of some other 
    	(opposite) area, but not necessarily. Although tilting can 
    	in theory occur along any line in the plane, it makes sense 
    	(at least initially) to look at what happens when the tilt 
    	lines coincide with the x and y axes in the graph.
    </para>
    <para>
    	What follows, then, is a brief examination of means by which 
    	a MUD can be adjusted so as to favour the various extremes 
    	of the interest graph, and what would happen if each 
    	approach were taken to the limit:
    </para>
    
    
    	<sect2 id="players">
  		<title>Players</title>
    	<para>
    		Putting the emphasis on players rather than the game is 
    		easy &mdash; you just provide the system with lots of 
    		communication commands and precious little else. The 
    		more the scales are tipped towards players, though, the 
    		less of a MUD you have and the more of a CB-style 
    		chatline. Beyond a certain point, the game can't provide 
    		a context for communication, and it ceases to be a 
    		viable virtual world: it's just a comms channel for the 
    		real world. At this stage, when all sense of 
    		elsewhere-presence is lost, you no longer have a MUD.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="world">
  		<title>World</title>
    	<para>
    		Tilting the game towards the world rather than its 
    		inhabitants is also easy: you simply make it so big and 
    		awkward to traverse that no-one ever meets anyone in it; 
    		alternatively, you can ensure that if they do meet up, 
    		then there are very few ways in which they can interact. 
    		Although this can result in some nice simulations, 
    		there's a loss of motivation implicit within it: anyone 
    		can rack up points given time, but there's not the same 
    		sense of achievement as when it's done under pressure 
    		from competing players.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		And what use is creating beautifully-crafted areas 
    		anyway, if you can't show them to people? Perhaps if 
    		computer-run personae had more AI a MUD could go further 
    		in this direction<footnote><para>Mauldin, M. L. (1994). 
    		Chatterbots, TinyMUDs and the Turing Test: Entering the 
    		Loebner Prize Competition. Proc. 
    		AAAI-94</para></footnote>, but it couldn't (yet) go all 
    		the way (as authors of single-player games have 
    		found<footnote><para>Caspian-Kaufman, J. (1995). Sid 
    		Meier's CivNET: Instruction Manual Microprose, Hunt 
    		Valley, Maryland.</para></footnote>). Sometimes, you 
    		just do want to tell people real-world things &mdash; 
    		you have a new baby, or a new job, or your cat has died. 
    		If there's no-one to tell, or no way to tell them, you 
    		don't have a MUD.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="interacting">
  		<title>Interacting</title>
    	<para>
    		Putting the emphasis on interaction rather than action 
    		can also go a long way. Restricting the freedom of 
    		players to choose different courses of action is the 
    		mechanism for implementing it, so they can only follow a 
    		narrow or predetermined development path. Essentially, 
    		it's MUD-as-theatre: you sit there being entertained, 
    		but not actually participating much. You may feel like 
    		you're in a world, but it's one in which you're 
    		paralysed. If the bias is only slight, it can make a MUD 
    		more "nannyish", which newcomers seem to enjoy, but 
    		pushing it all the way turns it into a radio set. 
    		Knowledge may be intrinsically interesting (i.e. 
    		trivia), but it's meaningless unless it can be applied. 
    		If players can't play, it's not a MUD.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="acting">
  		<title>Acting</title>
    	<para>
    		If the graph is redrawn to favour doing-to over doing-
    		with, the game quickly becomes boring. Tasks are 
    		executed repeatedly, by rote. There's always monotony, 
    		never anything new, or, if these is something new, it's 
    		of the "man versus random number generator" variety. 
    		People do need to be able to put into practice what 
    		they've learned, but they also need to be able to learn 
    		it in the first place! Unless the one leads to the 
    		other, it's only a matter of time before patience is 
    		exhausted and the players give up. Without depth, you 
    		have no MUD.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    <para>
    	From the above list of ways to tilt the interest graph, a 
    	set of strategems can be composed to help MUD administrators 
    	shift the focus of their games in whatever particular 
    	direction they choose. Some of these strategems are simply a 
    	question of management: if you don't tell people what 
    	communication commands there are, for example, people will 
    	be less likely to use them all. Although such approaches are 
    	good for small shifts in the way a MUD is played, the more 
    	powerful and absolute method is to consider programming 
    	changes (programming being the "nature" of a MUD, and 
    	administration being the "nurture").
    </para>
    	
    <para>
    	Here, then, are the programming changes which administrators 
    	might wish to consider in order to shape their MUD:
    </para>
    
    <para>
		Ways to emphasise PLAYERS over WORLD:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
    	add more communication facilities
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        add more player-on-player commands (eg. transitive ones like 
        TICKLE or CONGRATULATE, or commands to form and maintain 
        closed groups of personae)
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		make communication facilities easy and intuitive
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		decrease the size of the world
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		increase the connectivity between rooms
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		maximise the number of simultaneous players
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        restrict building privileges to a select few
    </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		cut down on the number of mobiles
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
    
    <para>
		Ways to emphasise WORLD over PLAYERS:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
    	have only basic communication facilities
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        have few ways that players can do things to other players
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		make building facilities easy and intuitive
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		maximise the size of the world (ie. add 
		<emphasis>breadth</emphasis>)
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		use only "rational" room connections in most cases
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		grant building privileges to many
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        have lots of mobiles
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
    <para>
		Ways to emphasise INTERACTING over ACTING:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
    	make help facilities produce vague information
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        produce cryptic hints when players appear stuck
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		maximise the effects of commands (ie. add 
		<emphasis>depth</emphasis>)
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		lower the rewards for achievement
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		have only a shallow level/class system
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		produce amusing responses for amusing commands
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        edit all room descriptions for consistent atmosphere
    </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		limit the number of commands available in any one area
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		have lots of small puzzles that can be solved easily
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		allow builders to add completely new commands
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
    <para>
		Ways to emphasise ACTING over INTERACTING:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
    	provide a game manual
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        include auto-map facilities
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		include auto-log facilities
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		raise the rewards for achievement
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		have an extensive level/class system
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		make commands be applicable wherever they might reasonably 
		have meaning
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        have large puzzles, that take over an hour to complete
    </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		have many commands relating to fights
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		only allow building by top-quality builders
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
   
    <para>
    	These strategies can be combined to encourage or discourage 
    	different styles of play. To appeal to achievers, for 
    	example, one approach might be to introduce an extensive 
    	level/class system (so as to provide plenty of opportunity 
    	to reward investment of time) and to maximise the size of 
    	the world (so there is more for them to achieve). Note that 
    	the "feel" of a MUD is derived from the position on the 
    	interest graph of the MUD's players, from which a "centre of 
    	gravity" can be approximated. 
    </para>
    <para>
    	It is therefore sometimes possible to make two changes 
    	simultaneously which have "opposite" effects, altering how 
    	some individuals experience the MUD but not changing how the 
    	MUD feels overall. For example, adding large puzzles (to 
    	emphasise ACTING) and adding small puzzles (to emphasise 
    	INTERACTING) would encourage both pro-ACTING and 
    	pro-INTERACTING players, thereby keeping the MUD's centre 
    	of gravity in the same place while tending to increase total 
    	player numbers. In general, though, these strategems should 
    	not be used as a means to attract new players; strategems 
    	should only be selected from one set per axis.
    </para>
    <para>
    	The effects of the presence (or lack of it) of other types 
    	of players are also very important, and can be used as a 
    	different way to control relative population sizes. The 
    	easiest (but, sadly, most tedious) way to discuss the 
    	interactions which pertain between the various player types 
    	is to enumerate the possible combinations and consider them 
    	independently; this is the approach adopted by this paper.
    </para>
    <para>
		First, however, it is pertinent to discuss the ways that 
		players generally categorise MUDs today.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
    
    <sect1 id="social_versus_gamelike">
  	<title>The social versus gamelike debate</title>
  	<para>
    	Following the introduction of TinyMUD<footnote><para>Aspnes, 
    	J. (1989). TinyMUD [C]. <ulink url=
    	"http://ftp.tcp.com/ftp/pub/mud/TinyMUD/tinymud-pc.1.0.tar.gz"
    	>TinyMUD</ulink></para></footnote>, in which combat 
    	wasn't even implemented, players now tend to categorise 
    	individual MUDs as either "social" or 
    	"gamelike"<footnote><para>Carton, S. (1995). Internet 
    	Virtual Worlds Quick Tour: MUDs, MOOs and MUSHes: 
    	Interactive games, Conferences and Forums Ventana Press, 
    	Chapel Hill, North Carolina.</para></footnote>. In terms of 
    	the preceding discussion, "social" means that the games are 
    	heavily weighted to the area below the x-axis, but whether 
    	"gamelike" means the games are weighted heavily above the 
    	x-axis, or merely balanced on it, is a moot point. Players 
    	of social MUDs might suggest that "gamelike" means a 
    	definite bias on and above the x-axis, because from their 
    	perspective any explicit element of competitiveness is "too 
    	much". Some (but not most) players of gamelike MUDs could 
    	disagree, pointing out that their MUDs enjoy rich social 
    	interactions between the players despite the fact that 
    	combat is allowed.
    <para>
    </para>
    	So strongly is this distinction felt, particularly among 
    	social MUDders, that many of their newer participants don't 
    	regard themselves as playing "MUDs" at all, insisting that 
    	this term refers only to combat-oriented games, with which 
    	they don't wish to be associated. The rule-of-thumb applied 
    	is server type, so, for example, LPMUD is gamelike, MOO is 
    	social; this is despite the fact that each of these systems 
    	is of sufficient power and flexibility that it could 
    	probably be used to implement an interpreter for the other 
    	one!
    <para>
    </para>
    	Consequently, there are general Internet-related books with 
    	chapter titles like "Interactive Multiuser Realities: MUDs, 
    	MOOs, MUCKs and MUSHes"<footnote><para>Poirier, J. R. (1994). Interactive 
    	Multiuser Realities: MUDs, MOOs, MUCKs, and MUSHes. The 
    	Internet Unleashed, 1192-1127. SAMS Publishing, 
    	Indianapolis, Indiana.</para></footnote> and "MUDs, MUSHes, 
    	and Other Role-Playing 
    	Games"<footnote><para>Eddy, A. (1994). Internet After Hours 
    	Prima, Rocklin, California.</para></footnote>. This fertile 
    	ground is where the term 
    	"MU*"<footnote><para>Norrish, J. (1995). 
    	MU*s.</para></footnote> originates &mdash; as an attempt to 
    	fill 
    	the void left by assigning the word "MUD" to gamelike (or 
    	"player-killing") MUDs; its deliberate use can therefore 
    	reasonably be described as a political 
    	act<footnote><para>Bruckman, A. S. (1992). Identity 
    	Workshop: Emergent Social and Psychological Phenomena in 
    	Text-Based Virtual Reality. MIT Media Laboratory, Cambridge, 
    	Massachusetts.</para></footnote>.
    </para>
    <para>
    	This attitude misses the point, however. Although social 
    	MUDs may be a major branch on the MUD family tree, they are, 
    	nevertheless, still on it, and are therefore still MUDs. If 
    	another overarching term is used, then it will only be a 
    	matter of time before someone writes a combat-oriented 
    	server called "KillerMU*" or whatever, and cause the wound 
    	to reopen. Denial of history is not, in general, a wise 
    	thing to do.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Besides, social MUDs do have their killers (ie. people who 
    	fall into that area of the interest graph). Simply because 
    	explicit combat is prohibited, there is nevertheless plenty 
    	of opportunity to cause distress in other ways. To list a 
    	few: virtual rape<footnote><para>Dibbell, J. (1993). A Rape 
    	in Cyberspace. The Village Voice, December 21, 1993
    	<ulink url= 

"ftp://ftp.lambda.moo.mud.org/pub/MOO/papers/VillageVoice.txt" >A 
Rape in Cyberspace</ulink>
    	| Reid, E. (1994). Cultural Formations in Text-Based 
    	Virtual Realities. Dept. English, University of Melbourne, 
    	Australia.
    	<ulink url= 
    	
"ftp://ftp.lambda.moo.mud.org/pub/MOO/papers/CulturalFormations.txt" 
>Cultural Formations</ulink>
    	</para></footnote>; general sexual 
    	harrassment<footnote><para>Rosenberg, M. S. (1992). Virtual 
    	Reality: Reflections of Life, Dreams and Technology. An 
    	Ethnography of a Computer Society.
    	<ulink url=  	
    	
"ftp://ftp.lambda.moo.mud.org/pub/MOO/papers/ethnography.txt" >An 
Ethnography</ulink></para></footnote>; 
    	deliberate fracturing of the 
    	community<footnote><para>Whitlock, T. D. (1994). Fuck Art, 
    	Let's Kill!: Towards a Post Modern 
    	Community.</para></footnote>; vexatious 
    	litigancy<footnote><para>Whitlock, T. D. (1994b). 
    	Technological Hierarchy in MOO: Reflections on Power in 
    	Cyberspace</para></footnote>. Indeed, proper management of a 
    	MUD insists that contingency plans and procedures are 
    	already in place such that antisocial behaviour can be dealt 
    	with promptly when it 
    	occurs<footnote><para>Bruckman, A. S. (1994b). Approaches to 
    	Managing Deviant Behaviour in Virtual Communities. MIT Media 
    	Laboratory, Cambridge, Massachusetts.</para></footnote>.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Social MUDs do have their achievers, too: people who regard 
    	building as a competitive act, and can vie to have the 
    	"best" rooms in the MUD<footnote><para>Clodius, J. A. 
    	(1994). Concepts of Space in a Virtual 
    	Community.</para></footnote>, or who seek to acquire a large 
    	quota for creating ever-more objects<footnote><para>Farmer, 
    	F. R., Morningstar, C. &amp; Crockford, D. (1994). From 
    	Habitat to Global Cyberspace. Proc. CompCon-94, 
    	IEEE</para></footnote>. The fact that a MUD might not itself 
    	reward such behaviour should, of course, naturally foster a 
    	community of players who are primarily interested in talking 
    	and listening, but there nevertheless 
    	<emphasis>will</emphasis> still be killers and achievers 
    	around &mdash; in the same way that there will be 
    	socialisers and explorers in even the most bloodthirsty of 
    	MUDs.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Researchers have tended to use a more precise distinction 
    	than the players, in terms of a MUD's similarity to 
    	(single-user) adventure games. Amy Bruckman's observation 
    	that:
    </para>
    <para>
    	"there are two basic types [of MUD]: those which are like
        adventure games, and those which are 
        not"<footnote><para>Bruckman, A. S. (1992). Identity 
        Workshop: Emergent Social and Psychological Phenomena in 
        Text-Based Virtual Reality. MIT Media Laboratory, Cambridge, 
        Massachusetts.</para></footnote>
    </para>
    <para>
    	is the most succinct and unarguable expression of this 
    	dichotomy. However, in his influential paper on MUDs, Pavel 
    	Curtis states:
    </para>
    <para>
    	"Three major factors distinguish a MUD from an 
    	Adventure-style computer game, though:
    </para>
    <para>
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
    	A MUD is not goal-oriented; it has no beginning or end, no 
    	'score', and no notion of 'winning' or 'success'. In short, 
    	even though users of MUDs are commonly called players, a MUD 
    	isn't really a game at all.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        A MUD is extensible from within; a user can add new objects 
        to the database such as rooms, exits, 'things', and notes. 
        [...]
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		A MUD generally has more than one user connected at a time. 
		All of the connected users are browsing and manipulating the 
		same database and can encounter the new objects created by 
		others. The multiple users on a MUD can communicate with 
		each other in real 
		time."<footnote><para>Curtis, P. (1992). Mudding: Social 
		Phenomena in Text-Based Virtual Realities. Proc. 
		DIAC-92 
		<ulink url=
"ftp://ftp.lambda.moo.mud.org/pub/MOO/papers/DIAC92.txt" 
>Mudding: Social Phenomena</ulink></para></footnote>
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
    	This definition explicitly rules out MUDs as adventure games 
    	&mdash; indeed, it claims that they are not games at all. 
    	This is perhaps too tight a definition, since the very first 
    	MUD was most definitely programmed to be a game (I know, 
    	because I programmed it to be one!). The second point, which 
    	states that MUDs must involve building, is also untrue of 
    	many MUDs; in particular, commercial MUDs often aim for a 
    	high level of narrative consistency (which isn't conducive 
    	to letting players add things unchecked), and, if they have 
    	a graphical front-end, it is also inconvenient if new 
    	objects appear that generate no images. However, the fact 
    	that Curtis comes down on the side of "social" MUDs to bear 
    	the name "MUD" at least recognises that these programs are 
    	MUDs, which is more than many "MU*" advocates are prepared 
    	to admit.
    </para>
    <para>
    	This issue of "social or gamelike" will be returned to 
    	presently, with an explanation of exactly why players of 
    	certain MUDs which are dubbed "gamelike" might find a binary 
    	distinction counter-intuitive.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
    
    <sect1 id="player_interactions">
  	<title>Player interactions</title>
  	<para>
  		What follows is a brief explanation of how players 
  		predominantly of one type view those other players whom they 
  		perceive to be predominantly of one type. Warning: these 
  		notes concern <emphasis>stereotypical</emphasis> players, 
  		and are not to be assumed to be true of any individual 
  		player who might otherwise exhibit the common traits of one 
  		or more of the player classes.
    </para>
    <para>
    	The effects of increasing and decreasing the various 
    	populations is also discussed, but this does 
    	<emphasis>not</emphasis> take into account physical 
    	limitations on the amount of players involved. Thus, for 
    	example, if the number of socialisers is stated to have "no 
    	effect" on the number of achievers, that disregards the fact 
    	that there may be an absolute maximum number of players that 
    	the MUD can comfortably hold, and the socialisers may be 
    	taking up slots which achievers could otherwise have filled. 
    	Also, the knock-on effects of other interactions are not 
    	discussed at this stage: a game with fewer socialisers means 
    	the killers will seek out more achievers, for example, so 
    	there is a secondary effect of having fewer achievers even 
    	though there is no primary effect. This propogation of 
    	influences is, however, examined in detail afterwards, when 
    	the first-level dynamics have been laid bare.
    </para>
    
    
    	<sect2 id="achievers_achievers">
  		<title>Achievers v. achievers</title>
    	<para>
    		Achievers regard other achievers as competition to be 
    		beaten (although this is typically friendly in nature, 
    		rather than cut-throat). Respect is given to those other 
    		achievers who obviously are extraordinarily good, but 
    		typically achievers will cite bad luck or lack of time 
    		as reasons for not being as far advanced in the game as 
    		their contemporaries.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		That said, achievers do often co-operate with one 
    		another, usually to perform some difficult collective 
    		goal, and from these shared experiences can grow deep, 
    		enduring friendships which may surpass in intensity 
    		those commonly found among individuals of other groups. 
    		This is perhaps analagous to the difference between the 
    		bond that soldiers under fire share and the bond that 
    		friends in a bar share.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Achievers do not need the presence of any other type of 
    		player in order to be encouraged to join a MUD: they 
    		would be quite happy if the game were empty but for 
    		them, assuming it remained a challenge (although some do 
    		feel a need to describe their exploits to anyone who 
    		will listen). Because of this, a MUD can't have too many 
    		achievers, physical limitations excepted.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="achievers_explorers">
  		<title>Achievers v. explorers</title>
    	<para>
    		Achievers tend to regard explorers as losers: people who 
    		have had to resort to tinkering with the game mechanics 
    		because they can't cut it as a player. Exceptionally 
    		good explorers may be elevated to the level of 
    		eccentric, in much the same way that certain individuals 
    		come to be regarded as gurus by users of large computer 
    		installations: what they do is pointless, but they're 
    		useful to have around when you need to know something 
    		obscure, fast. They can be irritating, and they rarely 
    		tell the whole truth (perhaps because they don't know 
    		it?), but they do have a place in the world.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		The overall number of explorers has only a marginal 
    		effect on the population of achievers. In essence, more 
    		explorers will mean that fewer of the really powerful 
    		objects will be around around for the achievers to use, 
    		the explorers having used their arcane skills to obtain 
    		them first so as to use them in their diabolical 
    		experiments... This can cause achievers to become 
    		frustrated, and leave. More importantly, perhaps, the 
    		number of explorers affects the <emphasis>rate of 
    		advancement</emphasis> of achievers, because it 
    		determines whether or not they have to work out all 
    		those tiresome puzzles themselves. Thus, more explorers 
    		will lead to a quicker rise through the ranks for 
    		achievers, which will tend to encourage them (if not 
    		overdone).
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="achievers_socialisers">
  		<title>Achievers v. socialisers</title>
    	<para>
    		Achievers merely tolerate socialisers. Although they are 
    		good sources of general hearsay on the comings and 
    		goings of competitors, they're nevertheless pretty much 
    		a waste of space as far as achievers are concerned. 
    		Typically, achievers will regard socialisers with a 
    		mixture of contempt, disdain, irritation and pity, and 
    		will speak to them in either a sharp or patronising 
    		manner. Occasionally, flame wars between different 
    		cliques of socialisers and achievers may break out, and 
    		these can be among the worst to stop: the achievers 
    		don't want to lose the argument, and the socialisers 
    		don't want to stop talking!
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Changing the number of socialisers in a MUD has no 
    		effect on the number of achievers.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="achievers_killers">
  		<title>Achievers v. killers</title>
    	<para>
    		Achievers don't particularly like killers. They realise 
    		that killers as a concept are necessary in order to make 
    		achievement meaningful and worthwhile (there being no 
    		way to "lose" the game if any fool can "win" just by 
    		plodding slowly unchallenged), however they don't 
    		pesonally like being attacked unless it's obvious from 
    		the outset that they'll win. They also object to being 
    		interrupted in the middle of some grand scheme to 
    		accumulate points, and they don't like having to arm 
    		themselves against surprise attacks every time they 
    		start to play. Achievers will, occasionally, resort to 
    		killing tactics themselves, in order to cause trouble 
    		for a rival or to reap whatever rewards the game itself 
    		offers for success, however the risks are usually too 
    		high for them to pursue such options very often.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Increasing the number of killers will reduce the number 
    		of achievers; reducing the killer population will 
    		increase the achiever population. Note, however, that 
    		those general MUDs which nevertheless allow 
    		player-killing tend to do so in the belief that in 
    		small measure it is good for the game: it promotes 
    		camaraderie, excitement and intensity of experience (and 
    		it's the only method that players will accept to ensure 
    		that complete idiots don't plod inexorably through the 
    		ranks to acquire a degree of power which they aren't 
    		really qualified to wield). As a consequence, reducing 
    		the number of killers <emphasis>too</emphasis> much will 
    		be perceived as cheapening the game, making high 
    		achievement commonplace, and it will put off those 
    		achievers who are alarmed at the way any fool can "do 
    		well" just by playing poorly for long enough.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="explorers_achievers">
  		<title>Explorers v. achievers</title>
    	<para>
    		Explorers look on achievers as nascent explorers, who 
    		haven't yet figured out that there's more to life than 
    		pursuing meaningless goals. They are therefore willing 
    		to furnish them with information, although, like all 
    		experts, they will rarely tell the full story when they 
    		can legitimately give cryptic clues instead. Apart from 
    		the fact that they sometimes get in the way, and won't 
    		usually hand over objects that are needed for 
    		experiments, achievers can live alongside explorers 
    		without much friction.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Explorers' numbers aren't affected by the presence of 
    		achievers.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="explorers_explorers">
  		<title>Explorers v. explorers</title>
    	<para>
    		Explorers hold good explorers in great respect, but are 
    		merciless to bad ones. One of the worst things a fellow 
    		explorer can do is to give out incorrect information, 
    		believing it to be true. Other than that, explorers 
    		thrive on telling one another their latest discoveries, 
    		and generally get along very well. Outwardly, they will 
    		usually claim to have the skill necessary to follow the 
    		achievement path to glory, but have other reasons for 
    		not doing so (eg. time, tedium, or having proven 
    		themselves already with a different persona). There are 
    		often suspicions, though, that explorers are too 
    		theoretical in most cases, and wouldn't be able to put 
    		their ideas into practice on a day-to-day basis if they 
    		were to recast themselves in the achiever or killer 
    		mould.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Explorers enjoy the company of other explorers, and they 
    		will play more often if they have people around them to 
    		whom they can relate. Unfortunately, not many people 
    		have the type of personality which finds single-minded 
    		exploring a riveting subject, so numbers are notoriously 
    		difficult to increase. If you have explorers in a game, 
    		hold on to them!
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="explorers_socialisers">
  		<title>Explorers v. socialisers</title>
    	<para>
    		Explorers consider socialisers to be people whom they 
    		can impress, but who are otherwise pretty well 
    		unimportant. Unless they can appreciate the explorer's 
    		talents, they're not really worth spending time with. 
    		There are some explorers who treat conversation as their 
    		specialist explorer subject, but these are very rare 
    		indeed; most will be polite and attentive, but they'll 
    		find some diversion if the conversation isn't 
    		MUD-related or if their fellow interlocutor is clearly 
    		way below them in the game-understanding stakes.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		The explorer population is not directly affected by the 
    		size of the socialiser population.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="explorers_killers">
  		<title>Explorers v. killers</title>
    	<para>
    		Explorers often have a grudging respect for killers, but 
    		they do find their behaviour wearisome. It's just so 
    		annoying to be close to finishing setting up something 
    		when a killer comes along and attacks you. On the other 
    		hand, many killers do know their trade well, and are 
    		quite prepared to discuss the finer details of it with 
    		explorers. Sometimes, an explorer may try attacking 
    		other players as an exercise, and they can be extremely 
    		effective at it. 
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Explorers who are particularly riled by a killer may 
    		even decide to "do something about it" themselves. If 
    		they make such a decision, then it can be seriously bad 
    		news for the killer concerned: being jumped and trashed 
    		by a low-level (in terms of game rank) explorer can have 
    		a devastating effect on a killer's reputation, and turn 
    		them into a laughing stock overnight. Explorers do not, 
    		however, tend to have the venom or malice that true 
    		killers possess, nor will they continue the practice to 
    		the extent that they acquire a reputation of their own 
    		for killing.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		The affect of killers on the explorer population is 
    		fairly muted, because most explorers don't particularly 
    		care if they get killed (or at least they profess not 
    		not). However, if it happens too often then they will 
    		become disgruntled, and play less frequently.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="socialisers_achievers">
  		<title>Socialisers v. achievers</title>
    	<para>
    		Socialisers like achievers, because they provide the 
    		running soap opera about which the socialisers can 
    		converse. Without such a framework, there is no uniting 
    		cause to bring socialisers together (at least not 
    		initially). Note that socialisers don't particularly 
    		enjoy talking <emphasis>to</emphasis> achievers (not 
    		unless they can get them to open up, which is very 
    		difficult); they do, however, enjoy talking 
    		<emphasis>about</emphasis> them. A cynic might suggest 
    		that the relationship between socialisers and achievers 
    		is similar to that between women and men...
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Increasing the achiever/socialiser ratio has only a 
    		subtle effect: socialisers may come to feel that the MUD 
    		is "all about" scoring points and killing mobiles, and 
    		some of them may therefore leave before matters "get 
    		worse". Decreasing it has little effect unless the 
    		number of active achievers drops to near zero, in which 
    		case new socialisers might find it difficult to break 
    		into established conversational groups, and thus decide 
    		to take their play elsewhere.
    	</para>
    	<note><para>
    		Although earlier it was stated that this paper 
    		does not address people who play MUDs for meta-reasons, 
    		eg. to learn how to program, I believe that their 
    		empirical behaviour with regard to the actions of other 
    		players is sufficiently similar to that of socialisers 
    		for the two groups to be safely bundled together when 
    		considering population dynamics.
    	</para></note>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="socialisers_explorers">
  		<title>Socialisers v. explorers</title>
    	<para>
    		Socialisers generally consider explorers to be sad 
    		characters who are desperately in need of a life. Both 
    		groups like to talk, but rarely about the same things, 
    		and if they do get together it's usually because the 
    		explorer wants to sound erudite and the socialiser has 
    		nothing better to do at the time.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		The number of explorers in a MUD has no effect on the 
    		number of socialisers.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="socialisers_socialisers">
  		<title>Socialisers v. socialisers</title>
    	<para>
    		A case of positive feedback: socialisers can talk to one 
    		another on any subject for hours on end, and come back 
    		later for more. The key factor is whether there is an 
    		open topic of conversation: in a game-like environment, 
    		the MUD itself provides the context for discussion, 
    		whether it be the goings-on of other players or the 
    		feeble attempts of a socialiser to try playing it; in a 
    		non-game environment, some other subject is usually 
    		required to structure conversations, either within the 
    		software of the MUD itself (eg. building) or without it 
    		(eg. "This is a support MUD for the victims of cancer"). 
    		Note that this kind of subject-setting is only required 
    		as a form of ice-breaker: once socialisers have acquired 
    		friends, they'll invariably find other things that they 
    		can talk about.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		The more socialisers there are in a game, the more new 
    		ones will be attracted to it.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="socialisers_killers">
  		<title>Socialisers v. killers</title>
    	<para>
    		This is perhaps the most fractious relationship between 
    		player group types. The hatred that some socialisers 
    		bear for killers admits no bounds. Partly, this is the 
    		killers' own fault: they go out of their way to rid MUDs 
    		of namby-pamby socialisers who wouldn't know a weapon if 
    		one came up and hit them (an activity that killers are 
    		only too happy to demonstrate), and they will generally 
    		hassle socialisers at every opportunity simply because 
    		it's so easy to get them annoyed. However, the main 
    		reason that socialisers tend to despise killers is that 
    		they have completely antisocial motives, whereas 
    		socialisers have (or like to think they have) a much 
    		more friendly and helpful attitude to life. The fact 
    		that many socialisers take attacks on their personae 
    		personally only compounds their distaste for killers.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		It could be argued that killers do have a positive role 
    		to play from the point of view of socialisers. There are 
    		generally two defences made for their existence: 1) 
    		without killers, socialisers would have little to talk 
    		about; 2) without evil as a contrast, there is no good. 
    		The former is patently untrue, as socialisers will 
    		happily talk about anything and everything; it may be 
    		that it helps provide a catalyst for long conversations, 
    		but only if it isn't an everyday occurrence. The second 
    		argument is more difficult to defend against (being 
    		roughly equivalent to the reason why God allows the 
    		devil to exist), however it presupposes that those who 
    		attack other players are the only example of nasty 
    		people in a MUD. In fact, there is plenty of opportunity 
    		for players of all persuasions to behave obnoxiously to 
    		one another; killers merely do it more openly, and (if 
    		allowed) in the context of the game world.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Increasing the number of killers will decrease the 
    		number of socialisers by a much greater degree. 
    		Decreasing the number of killers will likewise greatly 
    		encourage (or, rather, fail to discourage) socialisers 
    		to play the MUD.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="killers_achievers">
  		<title>Killers v. achievers</title>
    	<para>
    		Killers regard achievers as their natural prey. 
    		Achievers are good fighters (because they've learned the 
    		necessary skills against mobiles), but they're not quite 
    		as good as killers, who are more specialised. This gives 
    		the "thrill of the chase" which many killers enjoy 
    		&mdash; an achiever may actually be able to escape, but 
    		will usually succumb at some stage, assuming they don't 
    		see sense and quit first. Achievers also dislike being 
    		attacked, which makes the experience of attacking them 
    		all the more fun; furthermore, it is unlikely that they 
    		will stop playing after being set back by a killer, and 
    		thus they can be "fed upon" again, later. The main 
    		disadvantage of pursuing achievers, however, is that an 
    		achiever can get so incensed at being attacked that they 
    		decide to take revenge. A killer may thus innocently 
    		enter a game only to find a heavily-armed achiever lying 
    		in wait, which rather puts the boot on the other foot...
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Note that there is a certain sub-class of killers, 
    		generally run by wiz-level players, who have a more 
    		ethical point to their actions. In particular, their aim 
    		is to "test" players for their "suitability" to advance 
    		to the higher levels themselves. In general, such 
    		personae should not be regarded as falling into the 
    		killer category, although in some instances the ethical 
    		aspect is merely an excuse to indulge in killing sprees 
    		without fear of sanction. Rather, these killers tend to 
    		be run by people in either the achievement category 
    		(protecting their own investment) or the explorer 
    		category (trying to teach their victims how to defend 
    		themselves against real killers).
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Increasing the number of achievers will, over time, 
    		increase the number of killers in a typically Malthusian 
    		fashion.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    
    
    	<sect2 id="killers_explorers">
  		<title>Killers v. explorers</title>
    	<para>
    		Killers tend to leave explorers alone. Not only can 
    		explorers be formidable fighters (with many obscure, 
    		unexpected tactics at their disposal), but they often 
    		don't fret about being attacked &mdash; a fact which is 
    		very frustrating for killers. Sometimes, particularly 
    		annoying explorers will simply ignore a killer's attack, 
    		and make no attempt whatsoever to defend against it; 
    		this is the ultimate in cruelty to killers. For more 
    		long-term effects, though, a killer's being beaten by an 
    		explorer has more impact on the game: the killer will 
    		feel shame, their reputation will suffer, and the 
    		explorer will pass on survival tactics to everyone else. 
    		In general, then, killers will steer well clear of even 
    		half-decent explorers, except when they have emptied a 
    		game of everyone else and are so desperate for a fix 
    		that even an explorer looks tempting...
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Increasing the number of explorers will slightly 
    		decrease the number of killers.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="killers_socialisers">
  		<title>Killers v. socialisers</title>
    	<para>
    		Killers regard socialisers with undisguised glee. It's 
    		not that socialisers are in any way a challenge, as 
    		usually they will be pushovers in combat; rather, 
    		socialisers feel a dreadful hurt when attacked 
    		(especially if it results in the loss of their persona), 
    		and it is this which killers enjoy about it. Besides, 
    		killers tend to like to have a bad reputation, and if 
    		there's one way to get people to talk about you, it's to 
    		attack a prominent socialiser...
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Increasing the number of socialisers will increase the 
    		number of killers, although of course the number of 
    		socialisers wouldn't remain increased for very long if 
    		that happened.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	
    	
    	<sect2 id="killers_killers">
  		<title>Killers v. killers</title>
    	<para>
    		Killers try not to cross the paths of other killers, 
    		except in pre-organised challenge matches. Part of the 
    		psychology of killers seems to be that they wish to be 
    		viewed as somehow superior to other players; being 
    		killed by a killer in open play would undermine their 
    		reputation, and therefore they avoid risking it (compare 
    		Killers v Explorers). This means that nascent or wannabe 
    		killers are often put off their chosen particular career 
    		path because they themselves are attacked by more 
    		experienced killers and soundly thrashed. For this 
    		reason, it can take a very long time to increase the 
    		killer population in a MUD, even if all the conditions 
    		are right for them to thrive; killer numbers rise 
    		grindingly slowly, unless competent killers are imported 
    		from another MUD to swell the numbers artificially.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		Killers will occasionally work in teams, but only as a 
    		short-term exercise; they will usually revert to 
    		stalking their victims solo in the next session they 
    		play.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		There are two cases where killers might be attacked by 
    		players who, superficially, look like other killers. One 
    		of these is the "killer killer", usually run by 
    		wiz-level players, which has been discussed earlier. 
    		The other is in the true hack-and-slash type of MUD, 
    		where the whole aim of the game is to kill other 
    		personae, and no-one particularly minds being killed 
    		because they weren't expecting to last very long anyway. 
    		This type of play does not appeal to "real" killers, 
    		because it doesn't cause people emotional distress when 
    		their personae are deleted (indeed, socialisers prefer 
    		it more than killers do). However, it's better than 
    		nothing.
    	</para>
    	<para>
    		The only effect that killers have on other killers is in 
    		reducing the number of potential victims available. 
    		This, in theory, should keep the number of killers down, 
    		however in practice killers will simply attack less 
    		attractive victims instead. It takes a very drastic 
    		reduction in the number of players before established 
    		killers will decide to stop playing a MUD and move 
    		elsewhere, by which time it is usually too late to save 
    		the MUD concerned.
    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    </sect1>
    
    
	<sect1 id="dynamics">
  	<title>Dynamics</title>
  	<para>
		From the discussion in the previous section, it is possible 
		to summarise the interactions between player types as 
		follows:
    </para>
    
    <para>
    	To increase the number of achievers:
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
          reduce the number of killers, but not by too much.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
          if killer numbers are high, increase the number of 
          explorers.
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
		To decrease the number of achievers:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
        increase the number of killers.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        if killer numbers are low, reduce the number of explorers.
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
		To increase the number of explorers:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
        increase the number of explorers.
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
		To decrease the number of explorers:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
        massively increase the number of killers.
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
		To increase the number of socialisers:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
        slightly decrease the number of killers.  
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        increase the number of socialisers.
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
		To decrease the number of socialisers:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
        slightly increase the number of killers  
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        massively increase the number of achievers.
    </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		massively decrease the number of achievers.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		decrease the number of socialisers.
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
		To increase the number of killers:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
        increase the number of achievers.  
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        massively decrease the number of explorers.  
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        increase the number of socialisers.  
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
		To decrease the number of killers:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
        decrease the number of achievers.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        massively increase the number of explorers.  
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        decrease the number of socialisers.  
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
    <para>
    	What are the dynamics of this model? In other words, if 
    	players of each type were to trickle into a system, how 
    	would it affect the overall make-up of the player 
    	population?
    </para>
    <para>
    	In the figure below, green indicates increasing numbers and 
    	red indicates decreasing numbers. A red line with a green 
    	arrowhead means that decreasing numbers of the box pointed 
    	from lead to increasing numbers of the box pointed to; a red 
    	line with a red arrowhead would mean that a decrease in one 
    	leads to a decrease in the other, and so on. The thickness 
    	of the line shows the strength of the effect: thin lines 
    	mean there's only a small effect; medium lines mean there's 
    	an effect involving roughly equal numbers of players from 
    	both boxes; thick lines means there's a great effect, 
    	magnifying the influence of the origin box.
    </para>
    <para>
    	<figure id="en_hcds_2">
              <title>The flow of influence</title>
              <graphic
                fileref="figures/en_hcds_2.gif"/>
            </figure>
    </para>
    <para>
    	From this, it can be seen that the numbers of killers and 
    	achievers is basically an equilibrium: increasing the number 
    	of achievers will increase the number of killers, which will 
    	in turn dampen down the increase in the number of achievers 
    	and thereby reduce the number of excess killers.
    </para>
    <para>
    	The explorer population is almost inert: only huge numbers 
    	of killers will reduce it. It should be noted, however, that 
    	massively increasing the number of explorers is the only way 
    	to reduce the number of killers without also reducing the 
    	player numbers in other groups. Because increasing the 
    	number of explorers in a MUD generally encourages others to 
    	join (and non-explorers to experiment with exploration), 
    	this gives a positive feedback which will eventually reduce 
    	the killer population (although recall the earlier point 
    	concerning how few people are, by nature, explorers).
    </para>
    <para>
    	The most volatile group of people is that of the 
    	socialisers. Not only is it highly sensitive to the number 
    	of killers, but it has both positive and negative feedback 
    	on itself, which amplifies any changes. An increase in the 
    	number of socialisers will lead to yet more socialisers, but 
    	it will also increase the number of killers; this, in turn, 
    	will reduce the number of socialisers drastically, which 
    	will feed back into a yet greater reduction. It is possible 
    	for new socialisers to arrive in large enough quantities for 
    	a downward spiral in numbers not to be inevitable, but it is 
    	unlikely that such a system could remain viable in over a 
    	long period of time.
    </para>
    <para>
    	This analysis of the dynamics of the relationships between 
    	players leads naturally to a consideration of what 
    	configurations could be considered stable. There are four:
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
    <listitem><para>
        Killers and achievers in equilibrium. If the number of 
        killers gets too high, then the achievers will be driven 
        off, which will cause the number of killers to fall also 
        (through lack of victims). If there aren't enough killers, 
        then achievers feel the MUD isn't a sufficient challenge 
        (there being no way to "lose" in it), and they will 
        gradually leave; new killers could appear, attracted by the 
        glut of potential prey, however this happens so slowly that 
        its impact is less than that of the disaffection among 
        achievers. Socialisers who venture out of whatever safe 
        rooms are available eventually fall prey to killers, and 
        leave the game. Those who stay find that there aren't many 
        interesting (to them) people around with whom to talk, and 
        they too drift off. Explorers potter around, but are not a 
        sufficient presence to affect the number of killers.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
        A MUD dominated by socialisers. Software changes to the MUD 
        are made which prevent (or at least seriously discourage) 
        killers from practising their craft on socialisers; incoming 
        socialisers are encouraged by those already there, and a 
        chain reaction starts. There are still achievers and 
        explorers, but they are swamped by the sheer volume of 
        socialisers. The number of socialisers is limited only by 
        external factors, or the presence of killers masquerading as 
        socialisers. If the population of socialisers drops below a 
        certain critical level, then the chain reaction reverses and 
        almost all the players will leave, however only events 
        outside the MUD would cause that to happen once the critical 
        mass had been reached.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    	A MUD where all groups have a similar influence (although 
    	not necessarily similar numbers). By nurturing explorers 
    	using software means (ie. giving the game great depth or 
    	"mystique", or encouraging non-explorers to dabble for a 
    	while by regularly adding new areas and features), the 
    	overall population of explorers will gradually rise, and the 
    	killer population will be held in check by them. The killers 
    	who remain do exert an influence on the number of 
    	socialisers, sufficient to stop them from going into 
    	fast-breeder mode, but insufficient to initiate an exodus. 
    	Achievers are set upon by killers often enough to feel that 
    	their achievements in the game have meaning. This is perhaps 
    	the most balanced form of MUD, since players can change 
    	their position on the interest graph far more freely: 
    	achievers can become explorers, explorers can become 
    	socialisers, socialisers can become achievers &mdash; all 
    	without sacrificing stability. However, actually attaining 
    	that stability in the first place is very difficult indeed; 
    	it requires not only a level of game design beyond what most 
    	MUDs can draw on, but time and player management skills that 
    	aren't usually available to MUD administrators. Furthermore, 
    	the administrators need to recognise that they are aiming 
    	for a player mix of this kind in advance, because the 
    	chances of its occurring accidentally are slim.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    	A MUD with no players. The killers have killed/frightened 
    	off everyone else, and left to find some other MUD in which 
    	to ply their trade. Alternatively, a MUD structured 
    	expressly for socialisers never managed to acquire a 
    	critical mass of them.
    </para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    </para>
    
    <para>
    	Other types could conceivably exist, but they are very rare 
    	if they do. The dynamics model is, however, imprecise: it 
    	takes no account of outside factors which may influence 
    	player types or the relationships between then. It is thus 
    	possible that some of the more regimented MUDs (eg. 
    	role-playing MUDs, educational MUDs, group therapy MUDs) 
    	have an external dynamic (eg. fandom interest in a subject, 
    	instructions from a teacher/trainer, tolerance of others as 
    	a means to advance the self) which adds to their cohesion, 
    	and that this could make an otherwise flaky configuration 
    	hold together. So other stable MUD forms may, therefore, 
    	still be out there.
    </para>
    <para>
    	It might be argued that "role-playing" MUDs form a separate 
    	category, on a par with "gamelike" and "social" MUDs. 
    	However, I personally favour the view that role-playing is 
    	merely a strong framework within which the four types of 
    	player still operate: some people will role-play to increase 
    	their power over the game (achievers); others will do so to 
    	explore the wonder of the game world (explorers); others 
    	will do so because they enjoy interacting and co-operating 
    	within the context that the role-playing environment offers 
    	(socialisers); others will do it because it gives them a 
    	legitimate excuse to hurt other players (killers). I have 
    	not, however, undertaken a study of role-playing MUDs, and 
    	it could well be that there is a configuration of player 
    	types peculiar to many of them which would be unstable were 
    	it not for the order imposed by enforcing role-play. It 
    	certainly seems likely that robust role-playing rules could 
    	make it easier for a MUD to achieve type 3) stability, 
    	whatever.
    </para>
    <para>
    	At this point, we return to the social/gamelike MUD debate.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Ignoring the fourth (null) case from the above, it is now 
    	much easier to see why there is a schism. Left to market 
    	forces, a MUD will either gravitate towards type 1) 
    	("gamelike") or type 2) ("social"), depending on its 
    	administrators' line on player-killing (more precisely: how 
    	much being "killed" annoys socialisers). However, the 
    	existence of type 3) MUDs, albeit in smaller numbers because 
    	of the difficulty of reaching the steady state, does show 
    	that it is possible to have both socialisers and achievers 
    	co-existing in significant numbers in the same MUD.
    </para>
    <para>
    	It's very easy to label a MUD as either "hack-and-slash" or 
    	"slack-and-hash", depending on whether or not player-killing 
    	is allowed. However, using player-killing as the only 
    	defining factor in any distinction is an 
    	over-generalisation, as it groups together type 1) and type 
    	3) MUDs. These two types of MUD should not be considered as 
    	identical forms: the socialising which occurs in a type 3) 
    	MUD simply isn't possible in a type 1), and as a result the 
    	sense of community in type 3)s is very strong. It is no 
    	accident that type 3) MUDs are the ones preferred 
    	commercially, because they can hold onto their players for 
    	far longer than the other two forms. A type 1) MUD is only 
    	viable commercially if there is a sufficiently large well of 
    	potential players to draw upon, because of the much greater 
    	churn rate these games have. Type 2)s have a similarly high 
    	turnover; indeed, when TinyMUD first arrived on the scene it 
    	was almost slash-and-burn, with games lasting around six 
    	months on university computers before a combination of 
    	management breakdown (brought on by player boredom) and 
    	resource hogging would force them to close down &mdash; with 
    	no other MUDs permitted on the site for perhaps years 
    	afterwards.
    </para>
    <para>
    	This explains why some MUDs perceived by socialisers to be 
    	"gamelike" can actually be warm, friendly places, while 
    	others are nasty and vicious: the former are type 3), and 
    	the latter are type 1). Players who enter the type 3)s, 
    	expecting them to be type 1)s, may be pleasantly 
    	surprised<footnote><para>Bruckman, A. S. (1993). Gender 
    	Swapping on the Internet Proc. INET-93</para></footnote>. 
    	However, it should be noted that this initial warm behaviour 
    	is sometimes the approach used by administrators to ensure a 
    	new player's further participation in their particular MUD, 
    	and that, once hooked, a player may find that attitudes 
    	undergo a subtle change<footnote><para>Epperson, H. L. 
    	(1995). Patterns of Social Behaviour in Computer-Mediated 
    	Communications. Dept. Sociology, Rice 
    	University.
    	<ulink url=
    	
"http://www.eff.org/Net_culture/Misc/web_social_behavior.paper"
>Patterns of Social Behaviour</ulink></para></footnote>.
    </para>
    <para>
    	As mentioned earlier, this paper is not intended to promote 
    	any one particular style of MUD. Whether administrators aim 
    	for type 1), 2) or 3) is up to them &mdash; they're all 
    	MUDs, and they address different needs. However, the fact 
    	that they are all MUDs, and not "MU*s" (or any other 
    	abbreviation-of-the-day), really should be emphasised.
    </para>
    <para>
    	To summarise: "gamelike" MUDs are the ones in which the 
    	killer-achiever equilibrium has been reached, ie. type 1); 
    	"social" MUDs are the ones in which the pure-social 
    	stability point has been reached, ie. type 2), and this is 
    	the basis upon which they differ. There is a type 3) "all 
    	round" (my term) MUD, which exhibits both social and 
    	gamelike traits, however such MUDs are scarce because the 
    	conditions necessary to reach the stable point are difficult 
    	or time-consuming to arrange.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
    
    <sect1 id="overbalancing">
  	<title>Overbalancing MUD</title>
  	<para>
  		Earlier, the effect of taking each axis on the interest 
  		graph to its extremes was used to give an indication of what 
  		would happen if a MUD was pushed so far that it lost its 
  		MUDness. It was noted, though, that along the axes was not 
  		the only way a MUD could be tilted.
    </para>
    <para>
    	What would happen if, in an effort to appeal to certain 
    	types of player, a MUD was overcompensated in their favour?
    </para>
    <para>
    	Tilting a MUD towards achievers would make it obsessed with 
    	gameplay. Players would spend their time looking for tactics 
    	to improve their position, and the presence of other players 
    	would become unnecessary. The result would be effectively a 
    	single-player adventure game (SUD?).
    </para>
    <para>
    	Tilting towards explorers would add depth and interest, but 
    	remove much of the activity. Spectacle would dominate over 
    	action, and again there would be no need for other players. 
    	The result of this is basically an online book.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Tilting towards socialisers removes all gameplay, and 
    	centres on communication. Eventually, all sense of the 
    	virtual world is lost, and a chatline or IRC-style CB 
    	program results.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Tilting towards killers is more difficult, because this type 
    	of player is parasitic on the other three types. The 
    	emphasis on causing grief has to be sacrificed in favour of 
    	the thrill of the chase, and bolstered by the use of 
    	quick-thinking and skill to overcome adversity in clever 
    	(but violent) ways. In other words, this becomes an arcade 
    	("shoot 'em up") type of game.
    </para>
    <para>
    	It's a question of balance: if something is added to a MUD 
    	to tilt the graph one way, other mechanisms will need to be 
    	in place to counterbalance it (preferably automatically). 
    	Otherwise, what results is a SUD, book, chatline or arcade 
    	game. It's the combination that makes MUDs unique &mdash; 
    	and special. It is legitimate to say that anything which 
    	goes too far in any direction is not a MUD; it is not 
    	legitimate to say that something which doesn't go far enough 
    	in any direction is not a MUD. So long as a system is a 
    	(text-based) multi-user virtual world, that's enough.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
    
    <sect1 id="summary">
  	<title>Summary</title>
  	<para>
    	To answer the questions posed in the preface:
    </para>
    <para>
    	Are MUDs
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
        games? Like chess, tennis, AD&amp;D?
    </para>
    <para>
    	Yes &mdash; to achievers.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        pastimes? Like reading, gardening, cooking?
    </para>
    <para>
    	Yes &mdash; to explorers.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
        sports? Like huntin', shooting', fishin'?
    </para>
    <para> 
    	Yes &mdash; to killers.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
		entertainments? Like nightclubs, TV, concerts?
	</para>
    <para>
    	Yes &mdash; to socialisers.
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
    </sect1>
    
    
    <sect1 id="endnotes">
  	<title>Endnotes</title>
    <para>
    	This paper is an April 1996 extension of an earlier article, 
    	"Who Plays MUAs"<footnote><para>Bartle, R. A. (1990a). Who 
    	Plays MUAs? Comms Plus!, October/November 1990 
    	18-19.</para></footnote>. As a result of this, and of the 
    	fact that I am not a trained psychologist, do not expect a 
    	conventionally rigorous approach to the subject matter.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Permission to redistribute freely for academic purposes is 
    	granted provided that no material changes are made to the 
    	text.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
    
	</article>