<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1251"?>

<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
  [
    <!ENTITY % global.entities SYSTEM
        "../../../include/global.xml">
    %global.entities;
  ]
>

<article lang="en">

  <articleinfo>

    <title>Constructive Politics in a Massively Multiplayer Online
    Roleplaying Game</title>
    <subtitle>

    </subtitle>
    <author>
      <firstname>Matthew</firstname>
      <surname>Mihaly</surname>
    </author>

    <copyright>
        <holder>Matthew Mihaly</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>
        All rights reserved.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para> <ulink url =
      "http://www.ironrealms.com/corp/cpmmorpg01.htm" >Constructive
      Politics in a Massively Multiplayer Online Roleplaying
      Game</ulink></para>
    </abstract>

    </articleinfo>


    <sect1 id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
        Politics are no doubt one of the most persistent and
        pervasive aspects of modern life. Since the days of
        Cleisthenes in ancient Athens, success in politics has
        conferred status, power, and often wealth upon its devotees.
        It consumes and often destroys those who seek it, but the
        lust for success in it seems unquenchable. Thus far, major
        Massively Multiplayer Online Role-playing Games (MMORPGs)
        have been slow to implement any politics besides very
        rudimentary. This is a shame, as the social engineering
        possibilities provided for by political systems are legion.
    </para>
    <para>
        The object of this essay is to lay out the basic reasons why
        an MMORPG should want a political system, and guidelines for
        designing and implementing a system to provide constructive
        politics in a massively multi-player online world. I'm not
        going to go into detail about any specific system, because
        nearly every functional detail will depend upon the
        particulars of your world.
    </para>
    <para>
        To begin with, I must define what I mean by "politics", and
        particularly, by "constructive politics". For our purposes,
        let us define "politics" as generally non-violent
        competitions for power over fellow man. Thus, this would
        include anything from the American presidential race, to
        'office politics'. On the other hand, I would not term the
        French Revolution, or the Austrian Wars of Succession, to be
        politics in this sense. 
    </para>
    <para>
        I should note that in this discussion I will focus mainly on 
        what you'd call state governments, or autonomous (at least 
        when you ignore the power of the admins) governments who 
        control a geographical area. Particularly, I'll be using the 
        city-state in the ancient Hellenic style as my examples, as 
        the largest governmental organizations in most MMORPGs with 
        political systems are functionally similar.
    </para>
    <para>
        What then, do I mean by "constructive politics"? I believe
        that political situations can often be categorized as static
        or dynamic. It's not merely a bivalent possibility of
        course, but a scale. On one end, there are completely static
        political situations, meaning that there is no competition
        whatsoever for power. Of course, as an absolute, that is not
        possible, unless it is a state of one. 
    </para>
    <para>
        Monarchies and tyrannies generally are static political 
        situations. There is some competition for power, usually of 
        the 'office politics' situation, with the various 
        individuals competing for the favor of the those above and 
        ultimately the top person, but in the end the only way to 
        truly change the government is through some sort of physical 
        force-based pressure against the installed government, 
        whether that government be a national, office, or household 
        government.
    </para>
    <para>
        Dynamic politics, on the other hand, are political
        situations where fluidity and whim are the rule of the day.
        A hypothetical system where elected officeholders are
        forbidden from holding office longer than one day, and could
        not compete for it on the day after their day of glory,
        would be an extreme example of a dynamic system,
        particularly if the electorate was large and diverse. I
        believe that in order to build and maintain a constructive,
        rather than a destructive, system of politics, one must
        build a dynamic system that is tempered with static
        elements.
    </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="admin_reasons">
    <title>Reasons To Implement A Political System, Admin
POV</title>
    <para>
        Why should you care about having a political system in your
        game? I've identified three broad, main reasons: binding
        players to your world, creating opinion leaders, and newbie
        assistance.
    </para>
    <para>
        Politics allow you to provide players with two very
        important, positive feelings: a sense of attainment, and a
        sense of ownership and control over their environment. By
        giving players methods by which to advance in a political
        hierarchy, provided there are rewards attached (which will
        be discussed later), you give players the important feeling
        of achievement as they climb the ladder of success. Further,
        as players gain power in your world, they begin the
        transformation from guest to owner (at least in their minds,
        and that is what is important).
    </para>
    <para>
        The second reason for having a political system is the
        facilitation of the creation of opinion leaders. What I mean
        by this are people who others look to for guidance and who
        influence others opinions. To some extent or another, anyone
        who isn't a complete hermit is at least a very minor opinion
        leader, as we all have friends, family, and associates who
        are influenced by us to some extent. 
    </para>
    <para> 
        What we are concerned with, though, is the ability to 
        manipulate the player-base without having to directly 
        manipulate every single player. By manipulating players who 
        have power over other players by virtue of their opinion, or 
        by virtue of their position of power (which tends to make 
        them an opinion leader), one can guide a world into 
        productive behavior patterns more easily.
    </para>
    <para>
        The final reason, from the admin point of view, for having a
        political system, is to provide incentives for established
        players to help newbies. If you create a system where the
        membership of an organization, and particularly the leaders,
        benefit from numbers of players and more importantly numbers
        of heavy players, the established players will work to
        orient the newbies and ultimately make them feel a part of
        your world.
    </para>
    <para>
      So, reasons for having a political system, from the admin
      point of view:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          A sense of attainment and ownership in the world
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Creation of opinion leaders
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Provide incentives for player-assistance of newbies
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="citizen_motivations">
    <title>Citizen Motivations For Civic Participation</title>
    <para>
        While it's well and good to say that there are a number of
        benefits to be had in having a political system from the
        admin point of view, we need to examine reasons why players
        would be motivated to participate in a political system.
        First, however, we need to understand why the citizens of
        such a system would care enough to participate. Without a
        citizenry that cares, a political system will fail. Let's
        first briefly list the reasons that motivate people to
        participate as a citizen, in real life systems. These would
        include:
    </para>
    <para>
        Fear of the current regime. An example of this is the old
        Soviet Union, which liked to brag that 99% of its citizens
        voted (under duress of course, and generally with only one,
        state-sanctioned choice).
    </para>
    <para>
        Comradeship. I use this as a blanket term for motivations
        that involve a feeling of connection to the other citizens.
        Leaders of countries with a strong sense of nationalism
        often use this feeling to motivate the populace.
    </para>
    <para>
        Public services. One of the most tangible benefits a citizen
        in modern states receives are services that the government
        has elected to provide, such as public roads, a legal
        system, security from foreign threats, and so on. Of course,
        it is the case that citizens who do not participate may
        nearly always still take advantage of these services, but
        many do feel obligated to participated due to taking
        advantage of the services.
    </para>
    <para>
        Glory by association. Rather intangible, but not to be
        discounted, the feeling of glory that citizens of a
        successful state receive can be a prime reason why people
        care about their state. Whether it is an ancient Roman's
        pride in its immense military and organizational success, or
        19th century Germany's pride in its cultural and
        intellectual prowess, or modern day American pride in its
        status as the sole superpower, glory by association is a
        powerful motivator.
    </para>
    <para>
        Desire for self-determination. People want to have a say in
        their governments, given the level of power they can have
        over citizens. It's no more complex than a nearly universal
        desire to have one's opinion count.
    </para>
    <para>
        It is the case, of course, that the reasons for a citizen in
        a MMORPG to care about being a citizen, will not be quite
        the same as in real life. Particularly, one cannot expect to
        use the element of fear too heavily. Unlike real life, where
        often the only way to disassociate yourself with the state
        you live in is suicide (I don't think I need to go into the
        significant psychological barriers to that method of
        escape), players in a mud can and will simply quit if they
        feel that what they believe to be their rights are being
        impinged upon too heavily.
    </para>
    <para>
        Further, regardless of what in-game age you have a character
        start at, you will never achieve the kind of rabid sense of
        obligation or nationalism that real governments can achieve
        through indoctrination from a very early age. Players come
        to MMORPGs with their fundamental values already ingrained,
        and trying to change that will just frustrate you and
        irritate the player.
    </para>
    <para>
        Although it is true that some players, particularly in an
        intensive role-playing environment set in a world with a
        pre-existing history of nationalism (Star Trek, Tolkien's
        Elves vs. Dwarves, etc), can play with nationalist fervor,
        these players will never suffer the kind of discomfort and
        unpleasantness that real nationalists will. In the course of
        role-playing of course, their characters may, but the
        players themselves are there to have fun and will not stay
        around forever supporting a hopeless cause, as people may
        who are engaged in real-life nationalist movements.
    </para>
    <para>
        Of course, there are similarities. Just as in real life,
        comradeship is a powerful motivator. However, this
        motivation only exists in any large degree when 
        out-of-character relationships (assuming there is some 
        element of role-playing in an MMORPG) are strong enough to 
        cause players to feel that they have real, interpersonal 
        relationships with the other players that far transcend the 
        characters themselves. A player must feel that what happens 
        to his friends character does, to some significant degree, 
        affect his friend. He must feel that if his friend's 
        character is harmed or disadvantaged, then his friend is
        actually suffering.
    </para>
    <para>
        Likewise, a player can be manipulated to care about being a
        citizen by allowing governments to provide services for its
        citizenry that the citizenry either cannot attain
        independent of a government, or which are significantly
        difficult to attain independent of a government. I will go
        into specific examples of this later.
    </para>
    <para>
        Glory by association is also a real reason which can be used
        to make players care. Even though the actual contribution of
        a citizen-player to the relative success of his government
        may be negligible, just like in real life, players will take
        significant pride in the success of a political organization
        to which they belong. This can be true even if the 
        player-citizen has absolutely no voice at all in his 
        government. Like sports fans in real life, people construct 
        psychological attachments to essentially unrelated 
        organizations, and the success or failure of these 
        organizations can cause powerful feelings of glory or shame.
    </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="why_lead">
    <title>Why Should I Lead?</title>
    <para>
        So, now I have given reasons why the citizenry of a
        political organization can be caused to care about the
        organization, but I have yet to explain why the leaders of
        such an organization would be motivated to take upon
        themselves the responsibilities of power. Unlike the
        motivations for citizenry participation in a political
        system, which differ in some respects between real life and
        an MMORPG, the motivations for participation by the leaders
        are fairly similar in both. Broadly, these are: power,
        glory, challenge, and a desire to help.
    </para>
    <para>
        Power needs little explanation, and is perhaps the prime
        motivation for the majority of political leaders, both in an
        MMORPG and in real life. People value power for a number of
        reasons, including for its own sake, for the ability to
        attract members of the opposite sex (particularly in the
        case of men), for the ability to profit financially from
        either legal or corrupt exploitation of the power (Roman
        governors of mineral-rich provinces such as Spain were
        particularly good at this), for the ability to exact revenge
        upon ones enemies, and so on. All of these reasons can
        motivate players in an MMORPG as well as in real life.
    </para>
    <para>
        Glory is the recognition by ones peers (your peers being
        those whose opinions you care about) of your success, or at
        least the perception by one that ones peers are honouring
        your achievements. For an excellent essay on the power of
        glory in MMORPGs, read Jonathan Baron's article entitled
        <ulink url=
        "http://www.gamasutra.com/features/19991110/Baron_01.htm"
        >"Glory and Shame"</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
        While I suspect that the desire to overcome challenges plays
        a smaller role in real life, I believe it can play quite a
        large role in terms of motivating political leaders in an
        MMORPG. The reason for this lies in the way that players
        tend to view success in a game. Conditioned to expect there
        to be at least some pre-defined goals in a game, some
        players will treat a political system as another of Raph
        Koster's 'Ladders of Success' (found in <ulink url =
        "http://www.legendmud.org/raph/gaming/laws.html" >the Laws
        of Online Gaming</ulink> document), and will measure their
        success by their rise in a hierarchical political system.
    </para>
    <para>
        The desire to help is, of course, what we wish all
        politicians were motivated by. As anyone who pays any
        attention to real life politics knows, it is generally an
        unfulfilled wish, often because of the high cost in time and
        money associated with attaining any office. Still, there are
        those individuals for whom the simple desire to help is the
        main reason why they seek office, and it behooves designers
        to ensure that there are roles for these people.
    </para>
    <para>
        Players lead because:
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            Power
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Glory
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Challenge
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Desire to help
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="meaning_creation">
    <title>The Creation of Meaning</title>
    <para>
        So, now I have described the reasons why politics can be
        valuable from a design and administrative point of view, the
        general reasons why a player-citizen may care about
        politics, and the reasons why anyone would bother seeking
        office in an MMORPG. Let's now begin to examine more
        specific methods for creating a system that can provide
        solutions to these three general categories of reasons. I'm
        not going to lay out a specific plan for creating such a
        system, because the details must largely depend upon the
        details of the rest of the MMORPG.
    </para>
    <para>
        The first and most important thing that you must consider
        when creating a political system is that it must have
        meaning. It's not enough to, for instance, set up an
        electoral system and create some offices to be run for. If
        the system has no meaning to the player- citizens, then any
        power that officeholders have over the citizens will serve
        no purpose except irritating and angering the citizens. You
        must create perceived benefit for the player-citizens.
    </para>
    <para>
        I discussed earlier what perceived benefits a player-citizen
        may find from a political system to which he is subject,
        namely public services, comradeship, and glory by
        association. Let's look at ways to create these perceived
        benefits for your players.
    </para>
    <para>
        The first, public services, is the proverbial carrot. By
        allowing your political organization to provide benefits
        that the player cannot get elsewhere, you provide an
        initial, concrete sense that political organizations are
        meaningful. The range of benefits that can be provided is
        large, but, like most details of a political system, will
        depend to a significant extent upon the details of the world
        within which the system is set.
    </para>
    <para>
        Broadly though, these services could be things like teachers
        who will only teach citizens, NPC security forces to protect
        citizens from their enemies, state-owned banks, state-owned
        shops, quests that take place within the city, state-run
        brothels, and so on. Anything that is moderately interesting
        or useful to the players can be used, and will help to
        create meaning for political organizations in the minds of
        the players, as long as whatever you are using can't be
        easily gotten elsewhere.
    </para>
    <para>
        The second, comradeship, is best realized via one, very
        important method: collective striving under threat. The
        players must be given the opportunity to experience fear for
        the survival of their organization, or at least for survival
        of their organization's pride. They need to strive together
        against credible threats, and for credible goals.
    </para>
    <para>
        There are really two emotions that we want to arouse in the
        players to accomplish the goal of comradeship: fear and the
        elation that comes from overcoming challenges. It's
        important to understand that by fear I don't simply mean the
        fear one feels when one looks out ones window in the morning
        to see Mongol hordes thundering towards that lovely little
        picket fence in your front yard that you spent last weekend
        painting. I also mean the fear of humiliation; the fear that
        comes when your hated rival bests you at something you both
        care about.
    </para>
    <para>
        The most obvious way to create this sort of unifying threat,
        which has numerous real-life parallels, is hostile foreign
        militaries. Creating a military system for your statist
        governments is a topic too complicated to go into here, but
        suffice to say that as long as your military system has
        potentially real negative effects for the citizenry of the
        victim political organization, and provided that the victim
        citizenry doesn't feel totally powerless to combat the
        threat, and further provided that there are perceived
        positive benefits to being a citizen (public services, etc),
        external threats can be a fantastic way to gel a citizen
        base into a viable sub-community within your MMORPG. 
    </para>
    <para>
        Fear is a powerful motivator. This fear can be useful, even 
        when the object of the fear triumphs. Providing that a 
        certain hope of eventual success remains among the 
        citizenry, the siege mentality that can come from being 
        beaten can really bind people together.
    </para>
    <para>
        One can create effects similar to a military system in this
        respect by establishing and making public certain yardsticks
        of success for competing political organizations. For
        instance, perhaps you might make public the total net worth
        of these organizations, and give some sort of minor reward
        to the citizenry based on the success of the political
        organization relative to competing ones. Alternatively, you
        could hold international competitions between your political
        organizations like the Olympics. The details aren't really
        that important. It's simply the element of competition and
        the fear of humiliation and defeat that matter.
    </para>
    <para>
        The second method of creating comradeship &mdash; the 
        experience of collective elation &mdash; also requires that 
        there be some sort of external threat or rivalry to the 
        organization over which the members may triumph. What this 
        threat or rivalry is isn't particularly important, but the 
        more the players fear or hate the thing providing the 
        threat, the more effective this will be. If you don't want 
        to set up a situation where one political organization must 
        lose, you could provide rivalries with NPC organizations (or 
        powerful individuals). The upsides to this are that no one 
        loses. The downside is that it is difficult to get players 
        to feel the kind of rivalry with NPCs that they do with 
        actual players. It takes a lot in terms of admin resources 
        to create an ongoing rivalry of this sort.
    </para>
    <para>
        A side benefit to the process of collective victory over an
        adversary is the final way I've identified to get your
        players to care about being a citizen, and that is glory by
        association. I liken this to the bandwagon effect that
        sports franchises experience when they are having a great
        season. Suddenly all the fans, even ones who were not fans
        until the team started winning, are having a great time
        being involved in the experience, despite having nothing
        whatsoever to do with overcoming the challenges the team has
        overcome. Similar effects can be seen in successful
        organizations in an MMORPG.
    </para>
    <para>
        Create meaning by:
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            Creating public services that the government can provide
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Unify the populace through fear and collective striving
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Ensure at least occasional collective victory
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="democracy_hierarchy">
    <title>Democracy and Hierarchy</title>
    <para>
        The next important thing to consider in constructing a
        political system is that it needs to be based on some sort
        of democratic or republican principles. I wrote earlier of
        the fact that players come to your MMORPG with their
        fundamental values pre-determined by factors out of your
        control. Given that the vast majority of internet users come
        from democratic cultures, it is folly to try to force them
        into a feudalistic or autocratic system. Now, of course you
        can call your system feudalistic, autocratic, communistic,
        or anything similar, but in reality, unless the users feel
        like they have a say in their government, they
        <emphasis>will</emphasis> be annoyed. This say doesn't have
        to be on the principle of one man, one vote, but it does
        need to give them the feeling that their opinion matters, or
        at least, if they meet certain, attainable requirements,
        their opinion will matter.
    </para>
    <para>
        When actually structuring your system, consider the
        importance of hierarchy. A hierarchy of governmental
        positions allows participants to climb the ladder of
        success, and it also makes for more vibrant politics. Now,
        for this hierarchy to have any use, it must have real,
        though limited, power over the citizenry, and ideally there
        should be a division of responsibilities.
    </para>
    <para>
        The reason that I advocate a division of responsibilities is
        that by doing so, you increase the number of players who are
        potentially interested in participating in the political
        system. I've seen games where the only position of power in
        an organization (in this case a city), was the mayor. So the
        only people interested in that kind of position were fairly
        ambitious players who yearned to be at the top of the food
        chain, with the most control possible. It's my experience,
        however, that these players are not in the majority. Many
        players want to participate, but they either don't feel they
        are ready to be in charge yet, or they simply have no desire
        to be in charge. Further, in many cases, even an ambitious
        player does not have what it takes to lead, but could still
        make excellent and valuable contributions to a political
        organization.
    </para>
    <para>
        There are really any number of ways to divide up
        responsibilities, but I would generally suggest using a
        division by function. You might immediately think of simply
        imitating the large-scale structure of a government, say,
        the American. In other words, divide things up into
        legislative, judicial, and executive branches. However, it
        is important to keep in mind that this is supposed to be
        fun. Mimicking a real, modern government is neither really
        going to be possible or desirable. Who wants to sit through
        endless budget hearings or worse yet, a US Senate
        filibuster? Streamline, and simplify.
    </para>
    <para>
        Since one of the explicit goals of a political system in an
        MMORPG is to glorify the participants, and since you do have
        an admin staff that can step in to stop extreme cases of
        citizen-abuse, you do not really need to worry as much as
        many modern governments do about the idea of checks and
        balances. Checks and balances exist to regulate the behavior
        of government in absence of external authority, but this is
        not a true concern in an MMORPG. Regardless of how much
        power you cede to the players, the admin staff necessarily
        can step in, preventing would-be Stalins from driving their
        own citizens to quit playing through repressive actions.
    </para>
    <para>
        To stop certain designers from going fits of apoplexy this
        idea, permit me to hastily add that admins stepping in to
        regulate government in this manner should be a last resort
        only, and hopefully never at all. In practice, due to the
        fact that you can permit people in a virtual world to pick
        up and move far more easily than is possible in real life,
        and thus can afford to tolerate more repressive government
        than you could if the barriers to moving were as high as
        real life, and due to the fact that you can set up your
        system so that some sort of civic mandate is required to
        continue to rule, there is almost no need to intervene. If a
        ruler is too repressive, his citizens will replace him or he
        will soon find himself ruling an empty and rapidly-failing
        city.
    </para>
    <para>
        Instead, then, of organizing your governmental systems to
        accommodate internal checks and balances, you can
        concentrate on organizing it in such a way that best
        fulfills the reasons for having a political system at all
        that I mentioned earlier, namely a sense of player
        attainment and ownership, plot control, and newbie
        assistance. A hierarchy that is meaningful can fulfill the
        sense of player attainment. Giving the officeholders some
        real power, of which I'll speak more in a bit, gives them a
        feeling of ownership in the world.
    </para>
    <para>
        Masses of citizens can be motivated to act in ways that
        contribute positively to the overall atmosphere of your
        world by making them care about their organization, and then
        creating goals applicable to the entire organization, such
        as triumph over a rival organization, etc. Newbie assistance
        can be provided for by ensuring that an organization
        benefits from increased numbers of players, and particularly
        from increased numbers of active, involved players.
    </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="power">
    <title>Power</title>
    <para>
        Possibly one of the most difficult aspects of constructing a
        political system is deciding how much potential power the
        government can have over the citizens. The government has to
        have some, or the system will have little meaning to anyone.
        But, if the government has too much, you risk either the
        government abusing it and irritating the citizens to the
        point where they may permanently leave your world, or having
        to emasculate the government by frequent admin interference.
        Interfere too much, and the system loses meaning, because
        the players begin to perceive their actions as being
        necessitated by admin demands rather than as being the
        result of their relatively free choice.
    </para>
    <para>
        Some things to consider when measuring the impact of power
        are: How intrusive is the power? One thing that players
        particularly hate is the feeling that their private, 
        out-of-character conversations are being spied upon. Giving 
        a player government the equivalent of unlimited wiretapping 
        is a bad idea.
    </para>
    <para>
        How difficult/punishing is it for a player to escape the
        authority of a repressive regime? If it's impossible to
        escape in-game, you force players to escape by leaving the
        game. If it's too easy to avoid the authority of a
        government, particularly within its geographical
        jurisdiction, then you may as well not have one. Oftentimes,
        if the political organizations are sufficiently discrete
        (meaning that there is limited social crossover between
        them), the cost of leaving the organization is kept
        sufficiently high simply because players do not like to
        leave their peer group.
    </para>
    <para>
        What kind of power might a government have over its
        citizens, or, more generally, those living, working, or
        merely being, in their jurisdiction? You might consider
        taxation and the regulation of commerce, some sort of
        judicial system, and police power to enforce both the
        dictates of the lawmakers and the decisions of the judicial
        system. Here one must be careful however. It's been my
        experience that players are less willing to accept taxation
        of their income than people are in real life. Much trickier
        to pull off are judicial and enforcement systems that
        players will view as fair.
    </para>
    <para>
        The construction of judicial systems has been the subject of
        extensive debate, to no satisfying conclusion, within the
        MMORPG design world. Three of the focal points of the
        disagreements are
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem><para>
            How to bring and hold those suspected of criminal
            activity to trial (whether that trial be by
            player-magistrates or player-citizen jurists),
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            How to conduct the trial itself, and
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            What punishments can be acceptably imposed upon the
            player found guilty?
        </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
        The problems are largely those not faced in a large degree
        by real-life systems, and they all involve deciding how
        much power to allow players to have over each other. I'm not
        going to go into the various proposals for solutions to this
        problem, but I will say that in my opinion, the most
        difficult judicial issue to deal with is the issue of repeat
        offenders. This is because it's my opinion that players
        should <emphasis>never</emphasis> be given the power to
        permanently and irreversibly harm another player.
    </para>
    <para>
        In real life, we deal with criminals who have repeatedly
        committed certain acts considered particularly heinous by,
        usually, permanent (or at least extremely lengthy)
        imprisonment, or execution. Neither of these are truly
        options in an MMORPG's political system. Permanent
        imprisonment would just cause the player to lose interest
        fairly quickly, and execution (which, unless the game in
        question has a permadeath system, is not the same as
        'killing' someone in the game), or, in the case of a game,
        deletion. Some would not doubt disagree with me, but I
        believe that limiting punishments of this magnitude to the
        administrators is wise.
    </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="civic_participation">
    <title>Civic Participation</title>
    <para>
        So let's say that by now, you've designed a system that
        takes all the aforementioned elements into consideration.
        You've planned out a hierarchy, you've given it some, but
        not too much, power over the citizenry. You've created
        external threats or rivals to help bind the citizens
        together, and you've given the government the power to
        provide valuable public services, to further create a sense
        that the government has worth. The citizens are able to
        regularly voice their approval of disapproval of their
        leaders, and the leaders stand to lose their jobs if enough
        citizens disapprove. Perhaps you've created a bureaucracy
        that is either elected or appointed, and divided up the
        responsibilities of the government by department (Department
        of Defence, Department of Interior Security, Department of
        Newbie Assistance, Department of the Treasury, and so on,
        for example). What's missing?
    </para>
    <para>
        Civic participation. So far, the only way we've given the
        citizens themselves a way to take part in politics is by
        voting, or some other method of expressing favour or
        disfavour of a leader (for an interesting system in which
        players announce approval or disapproval of a leader on a
        daily basis, rather than in a one-time vote, see the MMORPG
        <ulink url="http://www.darkages.com" >Dark Ages</ulink>.
        This, however, is not enough.
    </para>
    <para>
        You need to give the citizens opportunities to get involved
        on a more day to day basis. Perhaps they could work as aides
        to the officeholders, with some, but not all, of the powers
        that the officeholders have. Better still, create tasks that
        any citizen can perform that will help the city. Make it as
        arbitrary as you need.
    </para>
    <para>
        Maybe your governments need widgets. These widgets are in
        limited supply around the land, but all governments need the
        same widgets. Ensure ways exist to recognize the citizens
        who bring in the most widgets to help his or her government.
    </para>
    <para>
        Bang! You've created the external rivalry I spoke of
        earlier, you've provided a challenge for the players to
        overcome, you've made the citizens feel more a part of their
        'nation' (or whatever), and you've given an opportunity for
        them to be recognized by their leaders for their work.
    </para>
    <para>
        Another example, specific to the city or city-state type of
        government, would be creating a rodent problem within the
        city and setting it up so that an excess of rodents within
        the city has ill effects for the city (perhaps outbreaks of
        disease among player- citizens, or a lowering of morale of
        the NPC population, which would lower economic
        productivity). The city could offer bounties per rodent,
        which would likely be an excellent way for small players to
        help the city and be rewarded financially at the same time.
        Positive reinforcement.
    </para>
    <para>
        This leads us to the final, basic thing to think about when
        creating a political system: creating incentives to build
        successful citizens. By successful, I mean successful from
        your point of view (i.e. they stay customers of your
        business and enrich the world in such a way as to cause more
        people to become customers of your business) and successful
        from their point of view (i.e., they feel enriched and
        excited by you world).
    </para>
    <para>
        You can significantly reduce your cost of administration,
        and increase your rate of newbie retention, by setting up a
        system that inherently rewards organizations that take good
        care of its newbies. For instance, if your system has an
        element that depends upon players voluntarily donating money
        to their government, it's likely that the cities with more
        active, competent players will benefit.
    </para>
    <para>
        A word is necessary as to why I strongly advocate allowing
        player-governments to be responsible for some essential
        services. The obvious objection is that due to the
        discontinuous nature of most player's in-game lives (players
        regularly up and leave the game, take extended absences, and
        so on), it's dangerous to set up a situation where players
        are potentially deprived of services they need and desire.
    </para>
    <para>
        My response to this is that a political system shouldn't, in
        any case, require constant effort and attention on the part
        of the leaders. There may be benefit to the government if
        the leaders do work constantly and steadily, but in most
        cases this is expecting too much. In order to prevent a
        disruption of services that the players need and want (and
        in turn prevent your customer service lines from lighting up
        with complaining customers), simply ensure that more than
        one person in a government is capable of performing the
        duties that an office requires, and that in case of
        emergency, the players have the power, through a special
        election, or whatever means of selection your system uses,
        to replace the itinerant leader.
    </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="destructive_politics">
    <title>Destructive Politics</title>
    <para>
        I've mainly talked, thus far, about constructive and
        beneficial politics, but now I want to discuss some major
        pitfalls, that can lead to destructive politics. These fall
        mainly into three categories: Overly dynamic politics,
        overly static politics, and an inability to resolve
        disputes. I've touched on most of these earlier in the
        essay, so I will keep this brief.
    </para>
    <para>
        Overly dynamic politics mean that the system is too fluid
        and changes too frequently. When political leaders are cast
        in and out of office too often, it becomes difficult for
        them to establish themselves as opinion leaders, and provide
        good leadership for the player-citizens. Further, winning an
        election (or your equivalent of an election) loses meaning
        to the victor, because he knows he got swept in on today's
        whim, and probably will be out again on tomorrow's.
    </para>
    <para>
        It also gets tiring and repetitive to the citizens if a new
        election is taking place every day (note that the
        aforementioned system of very regularly expressing your
        preference that Dark Ages uses avoids this, despite frequent
        'voting'. Real-life systems have never used this on a large
        scale because of logistical details that are mainly
        nonexistent in a virtual world).
    </para>
    <para>
        Static politics result from a powerless citizenship, or from
        a system that makes it too difficult to replace the
        leadership. This is undesirable because it removes the
        climbing-the-ladder-of-success aspect (if you can't replace
        the leadership, then no one new has a shot at climbing the
        ladder). In practice, this can be created by making the
        requirements for voting too high.
    </para>
    <para>
        The final major pitfall to avoid is the lack of ability to
        resolve disputes. This is a well-known pitfall in MMORPGs as
        regards plot resolution, and the issues involved here are
        basically the same. Example: World X has a political system
        whereby the in-game governments can define the voting
        criteria for its citizens. The government of city A has
        decided that only those of the Tsol'aa race may vote. This
        greatly upsets members of the Human, Rajamalan, Horkval, and
        Dwarven races and they would like to do something about it.
        Clearly they can't vote the government leaders out, so their
        only options (short of bribing or convincing the Tsol'aa
        voters to force their leaders to change their policies) are
        leaving the organization, unless you institute a way by
        which a government may be forcibly overthrown via force.
    </para>
    <para>
        Leaving the organization is really not something you want to
        force the citizens to do in a case like this, because they
        may be leaving their homes, breaking their psychological
        attachment to the organization, and so on. These can be very
        stressful things to do for a player, and can damage his
        interest in your world.
    </para>
    <para>
        Another example of poor plot resolution would be an
        experience I had in an MMORPG I designed and run. This world
        has a system of city-states in the Hellenic style. Two
        city-states were continually at odds, but the military
        system had not yet been implemented. One city-state, Ashtan,
        seemed to be winning most conflicts between players, and
        generally had high morale. It's primary enemy, Shallam, had
        somewhat lower morale, due to some internal conflicts that
        prevented it from gelling as a community. The way the
        military system was set up, it rewarded those city-states
        who had very active and devoted governments far more than it
        rewarded any strategic ability on the part of the generals.
    </para>
    <para>
        In any case, quite soon, Ashtan had conquered probably 10x
        the amount of revenue-producing land as Shallam, and was
        literally at the gates of Shallam, ready to take it over. I
        had not anticipated this would happen that quickly, if ever,
        and I was caught with my pants down, because I had no way to
        resolve this. There was no way to "take over" a city, and
        simply letting Ashtan burn Shallam to the ground was not an
        acceptable solution. In the end, I had to solve it, rather
        lamely, by simply nullifying the effects of the system and
        putting the system on hold while it was redone. Clearly this
        is just about the worst way to handle plot resolution, as it
        irritated the victors, and made the losers feel as if they
        didn't need to try next time, because the administration
        would rescue them.
    </para>
    <para>
        In retrospect, the major problem was that the Shallam
        citizens did not care enough. They didn't feel like there
        was enough reason to care whether they won or lost, and once
        Ashtan got rolling, the attitude that "We can't do anything
        about it." quickly prevailed. These were largely the results
        of an improperly constructed political system. There wasn't
        enough perceived benefit to being a citizen, and the major
        benefit that players saw was glory by association (which, of
        course, doesn't do much for those presently losing a
        conflict). So, the external threat posed to Shallam by
        Ashtan wasn't effective, because the citizens of Shallam
        didn't feel attached to Shallam.
    </para>
    <para>
        Major pitfalls:
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            An overly dynamic system
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            An overly static system
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            An inability to resolve disputes
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="conclusion">
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <para>
        I believe that I've elucidated the fundamental reasons and
        requirements for having an in-game political system in your
        MMORPG. It is useful from the administrative point of view
        because it is something interesting for your players to do,
        it binds communities together, and it can help reduce the
        cost of administrative support for newbies. It is viewed as
        useful to the players because they can achieve glory,
        because their friends are involved (circular, I know), and
        because they can gain services they could not otherwise gain
        through it.
    </para>
    <para>
        On a less practical level, political systems in virtual
        worlds are fascinating both to the creators and the players.
        Those in my MMORPG often comment that the intensity of
        politics are their favourite thing about it.
    </para>
    <para>
        There's something very, well, for lack of a better word,
        cool, about political interactions. I've watched people who
        started off as meek, seemingly weak players blossom into
        lions when the burden of leadership was placed upon them.
        I've seen problem players become responsible and valued
        leaders who, through their actions, also improved the
        experiences of those who followed them. Finally, few
        conflicts and storylines are more exciting to watch and
        arouse more passion in the participants than those of
        nations at odds. Without a political system, all you have is
        a bunch of informally aligned players clashing. But give
        these players a formal framework to work within, and
        suddenly players are making nobler sacrifices and deeper
        efforts than most of them ever would make if only their own
        welfare was at stake.
    </para>
    <para>
        This essay has merely scratched the surface I'm sure,
        particularly as so far, MMORPG political systems have been
        fairly rudimentary. I have little doubt, however, that as
        successive generations of MMORPGs are created, politics will
        become a more integral part of the design process. I expect
        to see systems with features that have not been tried on any
        large scale. For instance, systems where the players can,
        without admin assistance, determine their form of
        government, be it direct democracy, republicanism,
        plutocracy (rule by the rich), communism, 
        anarcho-capitalism, or whatever!
    </para>
    <para>
        Social engineering in virtual communities is already a
        nascent field of study, and as research into it progresses
        (certainly beyond the meager scope of this essay), I believe
        we're going to see these political systems become more
        sophisticated and more dominant (along with other, somewhat
        related systems, like economics) in game design. We have the
        technology. We can build them.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    </article>