<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1251"?>

<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
  [
    <!ENTITY % global.entities SYSTEM
        "../../../include/global.xml">
    %global.entities;
  ]
>

<!--
  Attention! If you have your local version of DTD
  Docbook on your computer, replace this line
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
  with this one
    "file:/path_to_dtd/docbookx.dtd"

  (If you use eDE from e-novative, than replace with this one
    "file:/c:/docbook/dtd/docbookx.dtd")
-->

<article lang="en">

  <articleinfo>

   <title>Concept Document of MMORPG Ireon</title>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <othername>zak</othername>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>Version 1.1.0b</releaseinfo>


    <abstract>
      <para>
        This document reflects a development team’s view of MMORPG 
        Ireon's gameplay.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can find additional information at project’s forum. Also
        feel free to e-mail to <email>input@ireon.org</email>.
      </para>
    </abstract>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>ireon</keyword>
      <keyword>concept</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <copyright>
      &copyrightinfo;
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      &legalnotice_en;
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
      Ireon is a three-dimensional multiplayer online
      RPG for the Windows operational system on a PC platform. Game
      action is going to take place in a fantasy world where players
      would live in a virtual community.
    </para>
    <para>
      The project is entirely open-source and free-of-charge for
      all.
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Gamedesign Philosophy</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Game concept</title>
      <para>
        Game concept lies in a creation of a virtual world. Players’ 
        occupation in this world is not restricted to fights. The 
        world is developed to satisfy needs of different player 
        categories such as warriors, politicians, traders, crafters, 
        explorers and socializers. Another feature of a world would 
        be accent on a group gameplay. Players would either meet the 
        challenges as a group in one team or in several groups 
        opposing each other. In such kind of a system the role of 
        npc (mobs) is subsidiary: players need them only for some 
        hunting if there is no team available. The most interesting 
        gameplay is provided for groups of players.
      </para>
      <para>
        We regard the future world as a place where residents can
        occupy themselves with interesting affairs. Thus gameplay
        consists of mini-tasks every one of which offers gameplay
        for certain group of players. Some of the tasks are proposed
        for fighters (e.g. some quests), another ones are for
        socializers (talks in a tavern). The biggest and most
        interesting tasks we call <emphasis>pseudoquests</emphasis>
        (more about pseudoquests see below). One distinguishing
        feature of pseudoquests is that they happen by themselves,
        and player characters just join them. Another one is that in
        such pseudoquests players oppose other players in teams.
      </para>
      <para>
        The world of the game would be a fantasy one, but this fact
        doesn’t suppose the use of any fixed undoubted system or one
        source. The world is developing first for of all for needs
        of a gameplay, combining different rpg systems and worlds of
        different authors, combining realism and fiction.
      </para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>World size and saturation</title>
        <para>
          Game world (Novalia island) would be small but very
          saturated. We do not promise vast territories: the player
          would be able to cross the whole island afoot for about
          half an hour or even less, but the existing space would be
          filled with content to the maximum. Our approach to world
          design is providing width of functionality instead of
          increasing amount of the similar content.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </sect2>


    <sect2>
      <title>Players</title>
      <para>
        The game is developed for hardcore and moderate players.
        Enhanced possibilities of players’ interaction and
        simplicity of use (which is one of the main priorities
        during the game development) may possibly attract some
        players from mass sector. The game is designed for the
        players who are at least 14 years old.
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Game description</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Genre</title>
      <para>
        Three-dimensional fantasy online multiplayer RPG (MMORPG).
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>General description of gameplay</title>
      <para>
        Game process consists of management of player’s character
        and use of this character for carrying-out certain actions,
        such as
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          conducting fights, fulfilling quests;
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          trade;
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          intercourse with other players;
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          crafting;
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          world exploration;
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          politics.
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The game will take place in a uniform three-dimensional
        world (island of Novalia). Therefore there will be no
        "locations" in the game, the player will be able to move
        through all accessible world at once.
      </para>
      <para>
        All of the game actions will happen in a real time and a
        three-dimensional space. The exception will be made only for
        certain actions like crafting or things’ exchange that are
        carried out using special interfaces.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Main gameplay features</title>
      <sect3>
        <title>Look and control</title>
        <para>
          There will be first-person and third-person look in the
          game. The player will be able to switch between the two
          views. Third-person look will have the sufficient
          mobility, the player will be able to change the angle of
          view, a direction and a distance to the character.
        </para>
        <para>
          The player will operate the character using 'point-and-
          click' system. Thus operating the mouse player moves the
          cursor on the screen and decided the place he wants the
          character to go or a character to attack. Also using
          cursor player gets access to in-game menus and other
          interface elements. Keyboard operation of character will
          also be supported.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Pseudoquests</title>
        <para>
          Based on a principle of mini-games we introduced special 
          term and that is pseudoquests. The most interesting 
          mini-games in the world of Ireon are called pseudoquests. 
          Pseudoquests have two basic qualitites: they are 
          self-sufficient and players who participate in them 
          oppose other players.
        </para>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Self-suffiency</title>
          <para>
            Pseudoquests exist without players. Pseudoquests are
            generated by system and serve as a lure for players, the
            task they can solve. Of course, without players
            pseudoquests are of no interest. But as they work by
            themselves players are free to join actions
            performed by AI and get fun and benefit for their
            characters.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Players' confrontation</title>
          <para>
            The majority of the pseudoquests would be designed for
            two teams of players, and those teams would compete for
            quest completion. Usually this can be achieved by
            setting opposite reqirements for quest accomplishment.
            Players can join pseudoquest by their will and they can
            choose the side also by their will. Cooperation between
            the members of one team significantly influences the
            final result of their actions for quest completion. Thus
            you may say that cooperation is a key factor while
            fulfilling pseudoquests.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Freedom of choice for players</title>
        <para>
          We hold the opinion that players should be able to choose
          gameplay to one’s liking regardless of character’s stats
          and that players should be able to change their choice
          while not creating new character. That’s why we do not
          have usual ‘levels’ for characters and stats binded to
          them: the possibility of making an action depends on
          skills of the character. That’s why in the war of states
          (see below) players take part voluntarily, and there is no
          race war (player is able to choose his side regardless of
          his character’s race). Also player would be able to choose
          freely if he wants to fight or participate in peaceful
          labor. Anybody will be able to make a career in a labor he
          likes to take part into.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Cooperation of players</title>
        <para>
          Players’ cooperation plays special role in the game. One
          would be successful most if he co-operates with others.
          Single play is an option, but most interesting features of
          the game are designed for a teamplay.
        </para>
        <para>
          In the game there will be lots of different interactions
          between players. But the main difference from analogues is
          that interactions in game will play useful functional role
          such as clans (see below).
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>War of states</title>
        <para>
          The most global and interesting pseudoquest from our point
          of view would be based on a full-scale war between two
          states. Thus, all the players are divided into four major
          groups: two conflicting sides, neutral side, and rogues
          that are hostile towards everybody. In accordance with
          principles of freedom of choice all the players may choose
          the side they want to play for regardless of their stats.
          Therefore if a player doesn't want to fight there will be
          a peaceful labor for him.
        </para>
        <para>
          Global pseudoquest based on magical springs capture is
          closely tied with war of states. It will give wide
          gameplay opportunities for its participants. It will be
          available only for characters with high stats. In this
          pseudoquest several teams from each of two sides will
          oppose each other. Players' interaction here will take on
          special significance. In detail this pseudoquest will be
          described in Software Requirements Specification.
        </para>
        <para>
          Most of the game will be related with war though this
          does not always mean only battles. But each citizen of
          island would feel impact of war on his own back.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Various forms of gameplay</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Character development</title>
        <para>
          Distinguishing feature of all players' in-game actions is
          that for their successful accomplishment players need not
          only the good in-game skills (i.e. character's stats) but
          also skills and knowledge of a real man in each specific
          situation. Unlike other RPGs where everything depends on
          numbers of stats in our game 'human element' plays
          significant role.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Military actions</title>
        <para>
          Major part of the military actions would be war between
          the states. Organization and carrying out of campaigns
          lies on players' shoulders for the most part. That is the
          players would organize and participate in raids whenever
          they want to do it. Game AI would encourage players to
          organize such campaigns. But, definitely, the most
          interesting part of warrior gameplay would be springs
          capture pseudoquest. It will be generated periodically
          (approximately once a week). It will include various
          actions to be executed by large numbers of warriors and
          mages. Battles with mobs would be of secondary importance.
        </para>
        <formalpara>
        <title>Murders</title>
        <para>
          Physical restriction on murder takes place only within
          city boundaries, all the other territories are
          theoretically free of such restriction. But in practice
          there are several in-game mechanisms making unlawful
          murder undesirable for a murderer. There are pc and npc
          police, carma and reputation and so on. It should be
          mentioned that all of this stuff applies only to murders
          of allies and neutral citizens, while murder of a
          character from an enemy state is considered a good and
          useful thing.
        </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para>
          Also players would be able to perform actions that are
          illegal in primary states (such as robberies and murders)
          in a special city-state Elbra. Elbra is a criminal haven.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Peaceful labor</title>
        <para>
          There would be large bifurcated trade system in game.
          Players would be able to exchange and trade with npc and
          other players, organize auctions or simply walk from town
          to town and offer their goods.
        </para>
        <para>
          Players would be able to create goods through crafting.
          This process would not only require from crafter to get
          "knowledge" within the game (as how to create some sort of
          thing in game), but also real knowledge of crafting
          process which is non-linear. Quality, characteristics and
          price of the thing would depend on the whole course of the
          crafting process. Experienced crafter would be able to
          make things that are specially tuned for their owner.
        </para>
        <para>
          Also player would be able to occupy himself with battle
          and healing magic, potions production, battles on special
          arenas with in-game money stakes, quest accomplishment,
          stealing, search for resources etc. Unique gameplay would
          exist for each profession, and it's not going to be like
          "click here, than click there". It would allow players to
          perform actions though various ways and evince one's
          keenness of wit.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Politics and a system of management</title>
        <para>
          Another form of character development in the game would be
          political activities. Players would be provided with large
          opportunities for self-government. Players would
          themselves take important decisions, which are going to
          have real impact on game world. Players would themselves
          create laws and see to their implementation, they would
          themselves (with a help of live team of course)
          organize various events.
        </para>
        <para>
          At the same time character who's executing government
          functions would receive wage, experience points and so on.
          Thus politics becomes alternative way of character
          development.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Professional associations</title>
        <para>
          In the game there would be professional associations of
          players called clans, which are going to be organized for
          executing of certain functions. Such associations would be
          aimed at exectuion of tasks that players would choose
          themselves while creating a clan. They would in no
          circumstances fight with each other.
        </para>
        <para>
          Clan is the group of the players which has publicly 
          offered some services. Players who need such services, 
          will know precisely the place to come to. Clan is an 
          analogue of a real world service firm. For example, there 
          would be clan of "seekers". Players that need some things 
          but for any reason can't get or find them may turn to such 
          a clan and for a contractual fee charge a clan member with 
          a work of search for those things.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Network opportunities</title>
      <para>
        There will be only a multiplayer mode in game, a single mode
        is not planned.
      </para>
      <para>
        Players will be able to establish their own servers on the
        computers connected to a LAN.
      </para>
      <para>
        The advanced opportunities will be built-in game for
        players’ intercourse such as a chat, a message system,
        thematic bulletin boards, etc. Also the game would have the
        developed system of services that would help novices to
        become acquainted with the game and join the gamers'
        community.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Key features</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>General</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
           Saturated completely three-dimensional island with no
           separate locations
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Trade and exchange
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Political system
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Non-trivial crafting system
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Four different races
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Four states and citizenship system
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Presence of different by means and aims forms of players
           associations
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Full-blown and convenient interface, easiness of
           familiarizing with the game
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Advanced in-game communicative systems
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           First and third person look with a free camera
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Battles</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
           Various warrior professions
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Main events for players are taking place in massive
           military campaigns, not minor internal skirmishes or
           quests
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Developed fightning system with a rich set of combos and
           tricks
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Three schools of magic
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Role system</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
           Classless system
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Reduced influence of levels on player's actions
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Five trees of professions
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Three levels of development in each profession
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Prorolling skills by training
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Additional</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
           The game is free-of-charge for players
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Completely open initial code
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           Anyone can establish his own server
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Platform</title>
    <para>
      The game will be developed for the PC platform. Development
      for other platforms currently is not planned. Developers will
      support the client for Windows OS, and server for FreeBSD.
      Developers will not support any other systems, but will help
      anyone who's willing to do it. Game will be played through the
      Internet. The virtual allocated server will be rented for the
      game. The game through the Internet for all users will be
      free-of-charge.
    </para>
    <para>
      Hardware requirements for client and server parts will be
      described later in Software Requirements Specification. Game
      will need at least 56 Kbit/s internet connecion speed.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Audience</title>
    <para>
      The game is designed for the players who are at least 14 years
      old. The game is intended for the Russian and English-speaking
      markets (two game versions in Russian and in English). Also
      game will be initially developed with the opportunities for
      further translation in different languages.

    </para>
    <para>
      Some games that are similar to Ireon in some aspects:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>
        World Of Warcraft
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Lineage II
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Planeshift
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Gothic
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        3sider.com
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

</article>
