<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1251"?>

<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
  [
    <!ENTITY % global.entities SYSTEM
        "../../../include/global.xml">
    %global.entities;
  ]
>

<!--
  Attention! If you have your local version of DTD
  Docbook on your computer, replace this line
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
  with this one
    "file:/path_to_dtd/docbookx.dtd"

  (If you use eDE from e-novative, than replace with this one
    "file:/c:/docbook/dtd/docbookx.dtd")
-->

	<article lang="en">

  	<articleinfo>

    <title>Concept Document of MMORPG Ireon</title>

    <releaseinfo>Version 1.2.1</releaseinfo>

    <abstract>
    <para>
        This document describes Ireon's gameplay in short.
    </para>
    <para>
        If you have any questions, feel free to ask them at
        project’s <ulink url="http://forum.ireon.org/"
        >forum</ulink> or via e-mail <email>input@ireon.org</email>.
    </para>
    </abstract>

    <keywordset>
    	<keyword>ireon</keyword>
    	<keyword>concept</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <copyright>
    	&copyrightinfo;
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
    	&legalnotice_en;
    </legalnotice>
  	</articleinfo>

  	<sect1 id="intro">
    <title id="intro.title">Introduction</title>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
        Ireon is a three-dimensional multiplayer online RPG for the
        Windows operational system on a PC platform. Game action is
        going to take place in a fantasy world where players would
        live in a virtual community.
    </para>
    <para>
        The project is open for anyone interested in development and 
        it is <ulink 
        url="http://www.fsf.org/licensing/essays/free-sw.html" 
        >free</ulink> for all.
    </para>
  	</sect1>
  	<!-- /Introduction -->

    <sect1 id="design_philosophy">
    <title id="design_philosophy.title">Game design 
    philosophy</title>
    <para>
        Game design philosophy is described in the <ulink
        url="http://www.ireon.org/en/docs/html/proposal.html"
        >Proposal</ulink>. In short its aim is to provide gameplay
        for players of different types and styles, whether they like
        fights and ratings, or socializing, roleplaying, and
        exploring the world.
    </para>
    <para>
        The game should support possible (and probable) change of
        player's interests during his living in a virtual world. It
        should provide convenient mechanisms for such a change and
        for a interaction and co-existence of players of different
        types in common areas.
    </para>
    <para>
        Thus game environment should constrain and restrict players
        to a minimal extent while encouraging positive and
        productive gameplay.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <!-- /Game design philosophy -->

    <sect1 id="game_description">
    <title id="game_description.title">Game description</title>

    <sect2 id="genre">
    <title id="genre.title">Genre</title>
    <para>
        Three-dimensional fantasy online multiplayer RPG (MMORPG).
    </para>
    </sect2>
    <!-- /Genre -->

    <sect2 id="physics_view_control">
    <title id="physics_view_control.title">Game physics, view and 
    control</title>
    <para>
        All game actions will take place in real time
        three-dimensional area, the only exceptions being some
        special interface actions such as crafting or exchange of
        goods.
    </para>
    <para>
        There will be first-person and third-person views in the 
        game. The player will be able to switch between the two 
        views. Third-person view will have the sufficient mobility, 
        the player will be able to change the angle of view, a 
        direction and a distance to the character.
    </para>
    <para>
        The player will operate the character using a 
        'point-and-click' system. Thus player will move the cursor 
        on the screen and choose a place he wants the character to 
        go or a character to attack. In a similar way player gets 
        access to in-game menus and other interface elements. 
        Keyboard control of character character will also be 
        provided.
    </para>
    </sect2>
    <!-- /Game physics, view and control -->

    <sect2 id="setting">
    <title id="setting.title">Setting</title>

    <sect3 id="game_world">
    <title id="game_world.title">Game world</title>
    <para>
        Ireon is a medieval fantasy world. Game will take place at
        Novalia isles (Novalia itself and a small 'satellite'
        Fjornell isle to the south). There will be no 'locations' in
        the game, the player will be able to move through all
        accessible world seamlessly.
    </para>
    <para>
        In Ireon 'real' creatures such as men and wolves will
        co-exist with fantasy ones such as orcs and dryads.
        Landscapes will vary from deadly mires and dense forests to
        vast plains and mountains. Novalia isle is divided into
        several regions by large rivers.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Game world -->

    <sect3 id="scenario">
    <title id="scenario.title">Scenario</title>
    <para>
        There would be no scenario in the game as such. The player
        will not be obliged to accomplish a certain chain of actions
        to be able to play. There will be only a prehistory of the
        world that would explain why everything in the world is as
        it is.
    </para>
    <para>
        It is possible, however, that sometime in future server's
        administration will carry out certain large events, that are
        going to 'advance' history and a world state.
    </para>
    <para>
        There will be minor quests in game, that will serve mainly
        as means of character development and money supply.
        The quests in our game are not main attractions for players,
        who would hopefully spend more time interacting with other
        players rather than with the mobs. Team quests are given
        much larger priority, than single person ones.
    </para>
    <para>
        The quests are going to be mostly of fedex-type variety.
        Players will be able to get assignments from certain npcs.
        It is possible that some quests will be organized in chains,
        so they become mini-scenarios.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Scenario -->

    <sect3 id="states">
    <title id="states.title">States</title>
    <para>
        There are four states at Novalia: Gillimor, Yiala, Kharum,
        and Elbra. Each state consists of one or more towns and
        surrounding territories. Characters of different races (see
        below) live in each of the states. There is also a concept
        of citizenship in our world &mdash; when character becomes a
        citizen of a state, that state provides him services
        (protection, discount at state-owned shops, etc.) in
        exchange for certain duties and obligations such as paying
        taxes.
    </para>
    <para>
        Each state has its own unique style, architecture, and
        culture. Gillimor is a typical medieval kingdom, while in
        Kharum there are more close-to-nature barbarians (though
        they are considered barbarians only in Gillimor). Yiala is a
        technocracy-like state, where science is almost a religion.
        City-state of Elbra is a shelter for criminals of all kinds.
        In a centre of Novalia isle there are Neutral lands, where
        player characters without citizenship can live in a free
        town of Allberg.
    </para>
    <para>
        Gillimor and Kharum are at war with each other, Yiala is
        neutral (as well as Neutral lands under Yiala's
        protectorate), while citizens of Elbra are not welcome
        anywhere.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /States -->

    </sect2>
    <!-- /Setting -->

    <sect2 id="roleplay">
    <title id="roleplay.title">Roleplay</title>

    <sect3 id="races">
    <title id="races.title">Races</title>
    <para>
        There are four playable races, that player can choose from
        for his characters: humans, dwarves, orcs, and elves. Each
        race has some unique features and predispositions to certain
        activities. The place of first appearance of a player
        character in a game world depends on its race. AI-controlled
        characters will react differently to characters of different
        races, though fundamental possibility of any action does not
        depend on character's race. Races actually have little
        impact on gameplay, rather giving little bonuses here and
        there. There might be characters of other races in game as
        well.
    </para>
    <para>
        There are no racial wars of any kind in Ireon. Heart of a
        conflict is a confrontation of multiracial states.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Races -->

    <sect3 id="basic_char_parameters">
    <title id="basic_char_parameters.title">Basic character 
    parameters</title>
    <para>
        Each character has basic numerical parameters. Result of
        almost any action in the world depends on there parameters.
        For example, strength, intellect and luck are among them.
    </para>
    <para>
        There is a system of experience points for development of
        these parameters. Character gets experience points for
        certain actions. This 'experience' is summed up with overall
        character 'experience'. When character's experience reaches
        a special milestone on a predefined scale (character
        advances to next 'level'), player gets points to distribute
        among his character's basic parameters. The impact of levels
        on other aspects of gameplay is minimal.
    </para>
    <para>
        Parameters can also be altered through magical means &mdash;
        scrolls, potions, spells. These changes may be temporary or
        permanent.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Basic character parameters -->

    <sect3 id="skills">
    <title id="skills.title">Skills</title>
    <para>
        The skills indicate how good a character can perform
        actions. The result of an action is the better the higher
        the corresponding skill is. Skills usually fit for a whole
        group of actions. Lack of a skill for performing certain
        action results in impossibility to perform that action.
        Possibility any given item's use also depends on having the
        appropriate skill.
    </para>
    <para>
        The skills may fall into one of following types:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>
        basic &mdash; these skills are given to all characters at
        the moment of their creation. These skills define actions
        that all characters need and players can not have a
        full-fledged game without them. Examples of such skills:
        short blades, light armor, basic magic, etc.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
        racial &mdash; some races may possibly have special skills
        inherent from birth. Example: maintenance of weapons for
        dwarves.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
        professional &mdash; character gets a chance to learn these
        skills after getting a certain profession. More about
        professions see below.
    </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        Skills can be altered through these ways:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>
        direct use &mdash; performing actions, that this skill is
        responsible for. The more character trains, the higher his
        skill becomes.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
        racial modifiers &mdash; some races give bonuses to some
        skills.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
        'magical means' &mdash; a skill can be raised by various
        potions, scrolls, etc. The effects may be temporary or
        permanent.
    </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Skills -->

    <sect3 id="abilities">
    <title id="abilities.title">Abilities</title>
    <para>
        Unlike skills abilities define an ability of a character to
        perform one specific action. Character can learn abilities
        for a fee from special npc-teachers. Other ways of learning
        new abilities are also possible.
    </para>
    <para>
        Magic spells or specific ways of weapon enchanting are
        examples of abilities.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Abilities -->

    <sect3 id="professions">
    <title id="professions.title">Professions</title>
    <para>
        A character does not need to choose his occupation once and
        for all in Ireon. There are no 'classes' in our world, we
        have professions instead. When a character learns a
        profession, he gets access to a set of skills (and abilities
        associated with those skills) that is peculiar to this
        profession. For example, when a character learns a 'basic
        blacksmith' profession, he may start to forge blades (he
        gets a 'forge blades' skill and several abilities such as
        'forge short knife' and 'forge short sword').
    </para>
    <para>
        It is up to a player which professions he wants his
        character to learn. At the beginning of the game, each
        character has access to four 'basic' versions of warrior,
        mage, craftsman and thief professions. Some professions may
        open access to other professions, that in turn may be an
        advancement of previous profession or a completely new area
        of knowledge. Thus a character may be a specialist in one or
        more professions, advancing earlier ones in the same field,
        or he may choose to combine several entirely different
        professions and become a 'ready-for-anything'-like person.
    </para>
    <para>
        A character may learn professions only at guilds (see more
        about them below). Overall number of professions that a
        character may get depends only on his intellect (the basic
        parameter one, not hacking-the-server variety).
    </para>
    <para>
        Characters that know certain professions, such as
        'blacksmith' or 'herbalist', can create their own game
        items. The rest has a choice to buy items from them or in
        shops or from other people.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Professions -->

    </sect2>
    <!-- /Roleplay -->

    </sect1>
    <!-- /Game description -->


    <sect1 id="gameplay">
    <title id="gameplay.title">Gameplay</title>

    <sect2 id="main_gameplay_features">
    <title id="main_gameplay_features.title">Main gameplay 
    features</title>

    <sect3 id="pseudoquests">
    <title id="pseudoquests.title">Pseudoquests</title>
    <para>
        The most interesting mini-games in the world of Ireon we
        term 'pseudoquests'. To be called a pseudoquest one should
        qualify as being a) self-sufficient and b) players who
        participate in it should oppose other players.
    </para>
    <formalpara>
    <title>Self-suffiency</title>
    <para>
        Pseudoquests exist without players. They are generated by
        system regularly and serve as a lure for players, the puzzle
        they can try to solve, the challenge they can accept. Of
        course, without players pseudoquests are of no interest. But
        as they work by themselves players are free to join actions
        performed by AI and have some fun and benefit for their
        characters.
    </para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
    <title>The confrontation between players</title>
    <para>
        The majority of the pseudoquests will be designed for two
        teams of players, and those teams would compete for a quest
        completion. Usually this is going to be achieved by setting
        opposite reqirements for quest accomplishment. Players can
        join pseudoquest by their will and they can choose the side
        also by their will. Cooperation between the members of one
        team significantly affects the final result of their
        actions. Thus you may say that cooperation is a key victory
        factor in pseudoquests.
    </para>
    </formalpara>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Pseudoquests -->

    <sect3 id="players_cooperation">
    <title id="players_cooperation.title">Cooperation between 
    players</title>
    <para>
        Cooperation between players plays special role in the game.
        One would be successful most if he co-operates with others.
        Solo play is an option, but most interesting features of the
        game are designed for a teamplay.
    </para>
    <para>
        There will be lots of different interactions between players
        in the game. But the main difference from analogues is that
        in-game interactions are going to play useful functional
        role. See more below.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Cooperation between players -->

    <sect3 id="war_of_states">
    <title id="war_of_states.title">War of states</title>
    <para>
        The most global and interesting pseudoquest from our point
        of view will be based on a full-scale war between two
        states. Thus, all the players are divided into five major
        groups: two conflicting sides (Gillimor and Kharum), two
        neutral sides (Yiala and Neutral lands), and rogues (Elbra)
        that are hostile towards everybody. In accordance with
        principles of freedom of choice all the players may choose
        the side they want to play for regardless of parameters or
        skills of their respective characters. Therefore if a player
        doesn't want to fight, we will find a peaceful labor for
        him.
    </para>
    <para>
        Global pseudoquest based on magical springs capture is
        closely tied with war of states. It will give wide gameplay
        opportunities for its participants. It will be available
        only for high-level characters. In this pseudoquest several
        teams from each of two conflicting sides will oppose each
        other. Interaction between players here will take on special
        significance. In detail this pseudoquest will be described
        in the <ulink
        url="http://www.ireon.org/en/docs/html/srs/index.html"
        >Software Requirements Specification</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
        Most of the gameplay will be associated with this war one
        way or another, though this does not necessarily mean only
        battles. But each and every inhabitant of Novalia will feel
        an impact of war on his own back.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /War of states -->

    <sect3 id="magic">
    <title id="magic.title">Magic</title>
    <para>
        Magic is not least of importance in our world. Three schools
        of magic are going to be helpful not only for mages, but
        herbalists and blacksmiths as well.
    </para>
    <para>
        One could learn magic at magic guild. Gillimor, Kharum and
        Yiala specialize each in its unique school of magic.
    </para>
    <para>
        Simple magic spells are going to be available to anyone in
        the world. Some of the most noticeable things of magical
        nature are teleports (maintained by magic guilds), healing
        springs, and various potions and amulets that affect
        character's organism.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Magic -->

    <sect3 id="communities">
    <title id="communities.title">Communities</title>
    <para>
        There are going to be several forms of communities for
        players to join: clans, guilds and parties.
    </para>
    <para>
        Clans are organized by players and consist of players only.
        Player can establish a clan just for a formal union with
        one's friends or develop it into a business organization. If
        the latter is the case, clan will need to acquire a license
        for each kind of activity. Then a state or other players
        will give assignments to clan and pay for their completion.
        Each clan will have a residence in one of the towns. A clan
        will have some means of group management and provide nice
        little bonuses to its members.
    </para>
    <para>
        For example, clan will be able to acquire
        'to-serve-and-protect' sort of license and help npc-patrol
        with that uneasy task; but unlike npcs clan members will
        have an option to chase criminal through the whole Novalia
        island. Another example is 'find-an-item' license. Players
        that are in need of certain game items but for some reasons
        can not find them (or get them from other player or mob) can
        turn to a clan for help &mdash; that is for a price, of
        course. Bonuses to reputation for every successfully
        accomplished assignment will stimulate clans to buy official
        licenses. Clans of one state are strongly discouraged to
        wage any 'wars' against each other &mdash; membership in a
        clan does not relieve anyone of citizenship
        responsibilities.
    </para>
    <para>
        Guilds are professional unions of characters. Guilds consist
        of both players and npcs. Guilds are managed by npcs. Guilds
        will provide jobs for those who doesn't want or can't join a
        clan. Guilds will also educate characters (let me remind you
        that one can learn professions only at guilds). Guilds are
        going to have public message boards, where anyone can leave
        a 'serious clan needs a serious mage'-like note. A guild
        will give its members discounts for any related supplies
        (cheap herbs for herbalists, cheap armor for warriors).
        Guilds in a same field are not going to be identical in
        different states, for example, Yiala's warrior's guild will
        educate archers better than the one in Gillimor or Kharum.
    </para>
    <para>
        Players also will be able to create and join parties &mdash;
        temporary unifying entity set up to ease realizing
        short-term goals such as hunting mobs or working in mines.
        Parties may play significant role as units of one force in
        time of great battles.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Communities -->

    </sect2>
    <!-- /Main gameplay features -->

    <sect2 id="gameplay_types">
    <title id="gameplay_types.title">Gameplay types</title>
    <para>
        Our virtual world is designed for different types of players
        and for each type we propose individual aims and ways to
        achieve them. The choice of way and role is always up to a
        player himself. Here are some possible aims depending on a
        player type:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>
        be best in something &mdash; there is going to be a large
        system of formal levels, points and so on, as well as
        detailed statistics of player actions; mage and warrior
        professions provide lots of opportunities to prove oneself a
        noble man;
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
        explore the world &mdash; here we've got non-trivial
        crafting and professions like herbalist and blacksmith;
        though game world is small in size, it will not feel like
        that thanks to locations highly varied in feel and look;
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
        socialize, create an extensive social network, just have a
        little rest after all &mdash; we provide a mud-like
        opportunities for socializing (politics, organizations
        managed by players, in-game press).
    </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect3 id="action_gameplay">
    <title id="action_gameplay.title">Action gameplay</title>
    <para>
        Major part of the action gameplay is going to be a war
        between the states. Organization and carrying out of
        campaigns lies on players' shoulders for the most part. That
        is, the players may organize and participate in raids
        whenever they want to.  But, definitely, the most
        interesting part of warrior gameplay is a 'magical springs
        capture' pseudoquest. It will be generated regularly
        (approximately once a week). It will include various actions
        to be executed by large numbers of warriors and mages.
        Battles with mobs are going to be of secondary importance.
    </para>
    
    <sect4 id="on_murders">
    <title id="on_murders.title">On murders</title>
    <para>
        Utter probition of murders exists only within city
        boundaries, all the other territories are theoretically free
        of such restriction. But in practice there are several
        in-game mechanisms making unlawful murder highly
        undesirable for a murderer. There are pc and npc police,
        carma, reputation, and so on. It should be noted that all of
        these measures apply only to murders of allies and neutral
        citizens. Murder of a character from an enemy state is
        considered a good and useful thing.
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <!-- /On murders -->
    
    <para>
        Fights between characters at special arenas with game
        money at stake is an option as well.
    <para>
    </para>
        Last but not least players have a choice of joining a dark
        side of the Force and becoming citizens of a criminal haven,
        a special city-state of Elbra. Citizens of Elbra can perform
        actions considered illegal in all other states, such as
        robberies and murders, with rather mild consequences.
    </para>

    <sect4 id="Combat system">
    <title id="Combat system.title">Combat system</title>
    <para>
        In-game combat doesn't differ from other actions, that is,
        the game doesn't switch to some special 'combat' regime.
        Combat takes place in real time with a free camera.
    </para>
    <para>
        During the combat defence (parrying the enemy blows) and
        continuous weak blows are done automatically. All strong
        blows, combos, stands, attack/defence priorities are
        executed  manually by players.
    </para>
    <para>
        At special arenas characters can participate in training
        fights (not to death) and fights for money. These last ones
        can be even hardcore (player who loses says goodbye to his
        character). Other players can watch the duel and make
        stakes. The winner and players who bet on him will get
        additional money.
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <!-- /Combat system -->

    </sect3>
    <!-- /Action gameplay -->

    <sect3 id="peaceful_labor">
    <title id="peaceful_labor.title">Peaceful labor</title>
    <para>
        There is going to be a large trade system in the game. The
        players will be able to exchange and trade goods with npcs
        and other players either tete-a-tete or through auctions.
    </para>
    <para>
        Players will be able to craft game items. To get good
        results the crafter will not only have to get 'knowledge'
        within the game (e.g. learn the appropriate profession and
        have necessary skills) but also he should understand the
        procedure of our non-linear crafting itself. This procedure
        will define the quality, characteristics, and price of the
        crafted item. An experienced crafter will be able to make
        things that are specially tuned for their owner to suit him
        best.
    </para>
    <para>
         Also player will be able to occupy himself with healing
         magic, production of potions, search for resources,
         gambling, etc.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Peaceful labor -->

    <sect3 id="politics_and_management">
    <title id="politics_and_management.title">Politics and 
    management</title>
    <para>
        Political activities provide yet another opportunities for
        character development in Ireon. Players are going to be
        self-governed to a large degree. Players will themselves
        take important decisions, and those decisions are going to
        have a real impact on game world. Players will create laws
        and see to their realization, they will (with a little help
        of live team, of course) organize various events.
    </para>
    <para>
        A character who's executing government functions will get
        wages, experience points, and so forth. Thus politics
        becomes alternative way of character development.
    </para>
    <para>
        Another highly social work is going to be a publishing of
        in-game press.
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <!-- /Politics and management -->

    </sect2>
    <!-- /Gameplay types -->

    </sect1>
    <!-- /Gameplay -->

    <sect1 id="key_features">
    <title id="key_features.title">Key features</title>

    <sect2 id="key_features_general">
    <title id="key_features_general.title">General</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            Completely three-dimensional seamless island with highly
            variable content
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Human-friendly interface
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Advanced in-game communicative systems
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            First-person and third-person views with a free camera
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <!-- /Key features: General -->

    <sect2 id="key_features_role">
    <title id="key_features_role.title">Role system</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            Four different races
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Classless system
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Flexible system of professions
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Reduced impact of levels on player's actions
        </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <!-- /Key features: Role system -->

    <sect2 id="key_features_gameplay">
    <title id="key_features_gameplay.title">Gameplay</title>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            Trade and exchange
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Political system and social life
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Citizenship system
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Non-trivial crafting system
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Several player communities, each with its own unique
            goals
        </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <!-- /Key features: Gameplay -->

    <sect2 id="key_features_combats">
    <title id="key_features_combats.title">Combats</title>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            Various warrior professions
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Major events for players are massive military campaigns
            rather than random skirmishes or quests
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Combat system with combos and feats
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Three schools of magic
        </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <!-- /Key features: Combats -->

    </sect1>
    <!-- /Key features -->

    <sect1 id="what_read_next">
    <title id="what_read_next.title">What to read next</title>
    <para>
        If you want to learn more about Ireon's game design, we
        recommend to turn to the <ulink
        url="http://www.ireon.org/en/docs/html/srs/index.html"
        >Software Requirements Specification</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
        If you are not exactly sure what do you want to read next,
        our <ulink
        url="http://bugtraq.ireon.org/wiki/en/Tutorials/Docs"
        >Documentaion Guide</ulink> may help you to make up your
        mind.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <!-- /What to read next -->

    </article>
    <!-- /Concept Document of MMORPG Ireon -->