<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1251"?>

<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
  [
    <!ENTITY % global.entities SYSTEM
        "../../../include/global.xml">
    %global.entities;
  ]
>

<article lang="en">

  <articleinfo>

    <title>I was young and I needed the money</title>
    <subtitle>

    </subtitle>
    <author>
      <firstname>Richard A.</firstname>
      <surname>Bartle</surname>
    </author>

    <copyright>
        <holder>Richard A. Bartle</holder>
    </copyright>
    <copyright>
        <holder>The Escapist magazine</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>
        All rights reserved.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para> <ulink url=
      "http://www.escapistmagazine.com/issue/43/3" 
      >I was young and I needed the money</ulink></para>
    </abstract>

    </articleinfo>


    <para>
    	So, it's the year 2000, at the height of the dot com boom. 
    	You've just been hired as Head of Online Games for a company 
    	with a paper value of over a billion dollars. You're 
    	promised a team of 30 people and as much time as you want to 
    	create the world's best massively multiplayer game world. 
    	What do you do?
    </para>
    <para>
    	What you <emphasis>should</emphasis> do is hire the first 30 
    	people you see on the street, irrespective of their skills, 
    	abilities or state of sobriety. What you 
    	<emphasis>shouldn't</emphasis> do is advertise, interview 
    	applicants, assess what they can bring to the project, and 
    	make appointments only after careful consideration.
    </para>
    <para>
    	The reason you should do the former is because that's what 
    	everyone else will do. Thus, when the company's directors 
    	realize that expansion is happening too quickly and they 
    	impose a recruitment freeze, you have all the job 
    	<emphasis>slots</emphasis> in place, if not any people who 
    	can actually <emphasis>do</emphasis> those jobs. You won't 
    	be calling a producer and telling him he should take his 
    	house off the market because we can't hire him after all, 
    	you'll just be replacing the Australian gap-year student you 
    	met playing snooker in a pub.
    </para>
    <para>
    	This explains how I was left to develop a virtual world with 
    	a team consisting of three programmers, a level designer and 
    	me, when there were six people officially working on the 
    	company's single-page WAP site.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Oh, we were given a more concrete deadline, too: one year. 
    	We were also given a budget: nothing.
    </para>
    <para>
    	What kind of massively multiplayer game could we write in 12 
    	months from a standing start, with only three programmers, a 
    	level designer and me? No producer, no artists, no QA; no 
    	design document, no tools, no middleware; no hardware, 
    	except our 700MHz PCs and a 250MHz server.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Hey, I know this one &mdash; we write a text game!
    </para>
    <para>
    	This <emphasis>did</emphasis> make horrible sense. I already 
    	had all that was needed to build and operate a textual 
    	world, because I'd spent 20 years building and operating 
    	them. It would be a push, but we could 
    	<emphasis>do</emphasis> this.
    </para>
    <para>
    	All we required was some fiendish mind-control system to 
    	persuade people to play a text game when they really wanted 
    	to play <emphasis>EverQuest</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para>
    	So, that would be sex, then.
    </para>
    <para>
    	I'd written a pitch for a sex MUD about five years earlier, 
    	but the funding fell through. Now was the time to dust it 
    	off! The thing is, sex in a text world has three things 
    	going for it that sex in a graphics world doesn't:
    	<itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
        	It's freeform. You don't have to motion-capture every 
        	position in the Kama Sutra and beyond, because people 
        	can animate it themselves using words.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
        	It's legal. You can write about antics that you would be 
        	jailed for depicting visually. The word is 
        	porno<emphasis>graphy</emphasis>, not 
        	porno<emphasis>texty</emphasis>.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
        	For a basic sex game to work, you need comparable 
        	numbers of both men and women. A female-friendly game, 
        	by virtue of its having women in it, is male-friendly; 
        	therefore, you need to attract women. And hey, guess 
        	what? Study after study has shown that, in general, 
        	women prefer words to pictures &mdash; especially when 
        	it comes to sexual fantasizing.
        </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
    	We toyed with the idea of creating a game for the gay 
    	market, on the grounds that there might be more homosexual 
    	male gamers than female gamers of any flavor, but 
    	unfortunately we were all straight so we weren't 
    	sufficiently engaged with the culture to know if this was 
    	indeed the case. When I approached the one gay guy in the 
    	office to ask him what he thought, he indignantly told me 
    	that he wasn't gay, and if I spoke another word on the 
    	subject he'd have me for harassment.
    </para>
    <para>
    	As luck would have it, around this time we noticed our level 
    	designer was female. This settled it: We decided to go for 
    	the broader market, as clearly one person is able to 
    	represent the views of 50% of the population with absolute 
    	accuracy. We'd program in functionality for non-straight 
    	encounters, but wouldn't build the game around them.
    </para>
    <para>
    	The atmosphere we strove to engender was one of wit and 
    	humor. Whether players would continue with this when they 
    	got down to business would be up to them, but we assumed 
    	they probably wouldn't. Humor was important for us, though, 
    	because it lightened the mood, giving a liberal and 
    	liberating "anything goes," fun impression. And, frankly, if 
    	you have to implement fetishes for opera gloves, headphones, 
    	feathers and being stuck in a car in a muddy field, well, 
    	how can you <emphasis>not</emphasis> inject humor into it?
    </para>
    <para>
    	The overall premise was that players were executives staying 
    	in a hotel in downtown Anonymous American City. While they 
    	were logged off, they'd be buying or selling or whatever it 
    	is executives do, their performance at which would be tied 
    	directly to how satisfied they were with their life. In 
    	other words, the better the sex they had in their time off 
    	(that is, while playing the game), the more money they'd 
    	make in their work time (that is, while logged off). They 
    	could spend this money on a better hotel room with better 
    	facilities and lots of clothes, toys and other goodies 
    	&mdash; so long as they could fit all these into their 
    	suitcase. This was so people who wanted, say, BDSM would 
    	visit a BDSM club and mix with other like-minded people, 
    	rather than kitting out room 419 with a rack and electrodes 
    	and sitting there glumly all alone.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Geographically, we arranged the world using the traditional 
    	grid system of every Anonymous American City. The hotel Blue 
    	Heights occupied the middle block, with two blocks on either 
    	side for us to fill with <emphasis>stuff</emphasis>. The 
    	further from the center you were, the more colorful the 
    	services on offer you were likely to find. Horizontal 
    	thoroughfares were numbered, from 69th Street (what else?) 
    	to 74th Street. Vertically were named (therefore themed) 
    	avenues: Peters, Queens, Great Union, Straight, Bohemia and 
    	Bacchus. Thus, if you wanted something to pep up your 
    	performance you might visit the Chinese medicine shop on 
    	73rd between Gt. Union and Queens, but if you just wanted to 
    	mail something to someone you'd go to the post office on the 
    	corner of Straight and 72nd.
    </para>
    <para>
    	We decided to allow some real-world illegal activities such 
    	as narcotics, but to make them losing strategies for 
    	gameplay. If you wanted to get high on cocaine and point a 
    	gun to a character's head, you'd get associated medical and 
    	police problems that would cost money to address and would 
    	never go away entirely. Still, if this is your bag, better 
    	you do it in a game than in real life. That said, consent 
    	was central to everything: Thus, no bestiality and no 
    	pedophilia. You can make love to a beanie baby (people do, 
    	I've seen the web sites), but not to a squirrel, no matter 
    	how much it's giving you that come-hither stare.
    </para>
    <para>
    	So far, so good, but you'll have noticed we were making some 
    	moral judgments here. Many people in real life insist on no 
    	sex before marriage; we, however, were condoning sex with 
    	people who were complete strangers five minutes previously. 
    	How did we make these decisions? Well, we basically 
    	determined to allow anything implementable, whether we 
    	ourselves were in favor of it or not, so long as it was not 
    	so emotive as to break "magic circle"<footnote><para> 
    	<ulink url= 
    	
"http://terranova.blogs.com/terra_nova/2004/01/but_is_it_play.html"
    	>But is it play?</ulink></para></footnote>: if any 
    	one of us felt something came with too much Reality, we 
    	didn't put it in. For example, some people &mdash; 
    	interestingly, many more women than men &mdash; have rape 
    	fantasies. Should we have implemented rape? Well, no, 
    	because that's too serious for a game. Even if characters 
    	were allowed to flag themselves as "rape-able," it would be 
    	too much. You're probably balking even reading about my 
    	discussing it, it's so emotive.

    </para>
    <para>
    	It was clear to us that not only should everything be 
    	consensual, but it should be personal to individuals: You 
    	could say, "These specific people are allowed to make love 
    	to me," but not, "Anyone in this room is allowed to make 
    	love to anyone else in this room." To this end, we 
    	implemented a fairly neat permissions system whereby every 
    	character had an attitude toward every other character. The 
    	default was <emphasis>stranger</emphasis>, which meant all 
    	physical contact was forbidden. Next was 
    	<emphasis>acquaintance</emphasis>, which allowed formal 
    	contact only. You could get to this stage either by setting 
    	it manually using a permit command, or by doing something 
    	that implied it; for example, proffering or accepting a 
    	handshake. From here we went to <emphasis>friend</emphasis> 
    	(non-intimate contact), <emphasis>boy/girlfriend</emphasis> 
    	(intimate contact), <emphasis>lover</emphasis> (sexual 
    	contact) and, for the sub/dom community, 
    	<emphasis>master/mistress</emphasis> (unrestricted &mdash; 
    	they could control you as a puppet if they wanted).
    </para>
    <para>
    	Sex in the real world has biological consequences, the main 
    	ones being sexually transmitted diseases and children. STDs 
    	were present only when curable; you might catch chlamydia, 
    	but not AIDS. Children, we completely ruled out as an 
    	option; characters might suffer gameplay-affecting 
    	is-she-pregnant anxiety after a wild night of unprotected 
    	sex, but it would last a (game) month at most.
    </para>
    <para>
    	As for the sex act itself, we implemented it using a 
    	modification of the classic MUD combat system. Before you 
    	get all uppity and insist that it's disgraceful to associate 
    	sex with fighting and I should not be allowed within looking 
    	distance of women for merely harboring such thoughts (and I 
    	have, indeed, had people say that), let me highlight the 
    	word <emphasis>modification</emphasis>. The mechanics are 
    	similar (automatic exchanges of interactions, qualified by 
    	inputs undertaken during the process), but that's where it 
    	ends. For example, in a combat MUD, your actions typically 
    	determine how many points you get; in this game, your 
    	actions determined how many points your 
    	<emphasis>partner</emphasis> got. In other words, your 
    	partner benefited from your sexual prowess, not you.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Lest you gain the impression that the only interesting thing 
    	about this game was its subject matter, I'd like to say, 
    	categorically, right here and now, that OK, you're probably 
    	right. As a designer, I was personally very excited by some 
    	of the concepts we developed, but there are probably fewer 
    	than 20 people in the whole world who would share my 
    	enthusiasm in this regard; sadly, therefore, there's not 
    	much point in my boasting about it. I would, however, like 
    	to mention our superb system for automatically monitoring 
    	the ability of body parts to function.
    </para>
    <para>
    	For instance, take room descriptions. They would change 
    	on-the-fly if you were unable to see or hear or whatever; 
    	commands which required the use of fingers (such as playing 
    	the piano) wouldn't work if your fingers were restricted 
    	(such as they would be if you were wearing mittens). This 
    	worked across all sensory modalities and all components of 
    	the body (and yes, male and female bodies did have some 
    	different components). It remains cutting-edge stuff for 
    	textual worlds, but of course only designers are likely to 
    	care much about it; as a player, you just want to play. The 
    	reason I mention it is that although it's something that 
    	would enhance all MUDs, it was developed specifically in 
    	response to a sex game requirement: bondage. If you're 
    	blindfolded and have a horse bit in your mouth, you can 
    	still make out some of the environment ("hmm, that feels 
    	like the heat from a branding iron") but you can't always 
    	perform everyday commands ("I'd shout for help if it weren't 
    	for this horse bit in my mouth").
    </para>
    <para>
    	Plus, I <emphasis>do</emphasis> want to boast, dammit!
    </para>
    <para>
    	I could continue for pages and pages, here. I could tell you 
    	about the fetish system, the mad cultists, the Little Black 
    	Book, how fashion worked, interactions with NPCs, layers of 
    	clothing ... but I can't right now, so I'll have to stop. I 
    	will say, though, for you designer types out there, we did 
    	account for my player types system, and I didn't advocate 
    	having permanent death...
    </para>
    <para>
    	But it all fell apart with some four months to go. Despite 
    	the fact we were on course to go into open beta by the end 
    	of our allotted year, the company didn't have a year's worth 
    	of money. Somehow, hiring 800 people on the strength of a 
    	business plan that could be paraphrased as "spend what we 
    	have and then figure out how to get some more" was not 
    	sustainable. We lost our jobs and the game went into 
    	mothballs.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Would it have worked? I was cautiously optimistic, even 
    	though there was no support in the company itself for the 
    	product. ("We can't be associated with sex games, only with 
    	violent games" &mdash; actual quote from a member of the 
    	sales team!) I don't think it would have been a huge 
    	storming success, but I figured we could have got maybe 
    	10,000 regular players within six months of opening &mdash; 
    	perhaps more, if AOL had banned it.
    </para>
    <para>
    	Would I do it again? Well, I'd certainly think about it. It 
    	raised some very interesting design issues that produced 
    	some highly novel solutions, which I'd like to see in 
    	action. The subject matter isn't itself remarkable, though: 
    	Rather like writing for a franchise, you can stray within 
    	the confines of the defined world, but you don't get to 
    	change the Unique Selling Points.
    </para>
    <para>
    	It beats the hell out of WAP, though.
    </para>

    </article>